<chapter label="" id="Class-_002d-Model-of-Communicating-Entities">
<title>Class, Model of Communicating Entities</title>

<anchor id="goldberg1"/><blockquote><attribution>Adele Goldberg</attribution>
<para>If I give you something that you can play with and extend, even a
piece of paper with a paragraph and I say it&#8217;s not written well,
rewrite it, that&#8217;s easier than giving you nothing and say make
something; you know, giving a blank sheet of paper and starting to
write.  So the lovely part that has proven true for professional
programmers as well as kids is when you start with something, an
object that does something, and then you put many objects like those
together and have them interact, and then you extend and make them
behave a little differently, you can take a very incremental approach
to learning how to control a computer system.
</para></blockquote>



<para>Cuis-Smalltalk is a pure object-oriented programming (OOP) language. All the
entities in the language: integers, floats, rational numbers, strings,
collections, blocks of code, and so forth &#8211; every instance usable as a
noun in Smalltalk &#8211; is an object.
</para>


<sect1 label="" id="Understanding-Object-Oriented-Programming">
<title>Understanding Object-Oriented Programming</title>

<para>But just what is an object?
</para>
<para>At its simplest, an object has two components:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Internal state.</emphasis> This is embodied by variables
   known only to the object. A variable only visible within the object
   is called a <firstterm>private</firstterm> variable. As a consequence, it is impossible
   &#8211; if the object decides so &#8211; to know the internal state of the object
   from another object.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">A repertoire of behaviors.</emphasis> These are the messages
   an object instance responds to. When the object
   receives a message it understands, it gets its behavior from a
   method with that name known by its class or superclass.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>subclass</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>instance</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>selector</primary></indexterm>
<para>The method name is called a <firstterm>selector</firstterm> because it is used to select
which behavior is invoked. For example, in <literal>'hello' at: 1 put: $B</literal>,
the method invoked has the selector <literal>#at:put:</literal> and the arguments
<literal>1</literal> and <literal>$B</literal>.  All selectors are symbols.
</para>
<para>Object instances are created &#8211; <firstterm>instantiated</firstterm> &#8211;
following a model or template. This model is known as its <firstterm>Class</firstterm>.
All instances of a class share the same methods and so react in the same ways.
</para>
<para>For example, there is one class <literal>Fraction</literal> but many
fractions (1/2, 1/3, 23/17, ...) which all behave the way
we expect fractions to behave.  The class <literal>Fraction</literal>
and the classes it inherits from define this common behavior,
as we will now describe.
</para>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>instance</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>instance variable</primary></indexterm>
<para>A given class declares its internal variables &#8211; states &#8211; and the
behavior by implementing the methods.  A variable is basically a named
box that can hold any object.  Each instance variable of a class gets its own
box with the common name.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>rational (fraction)</secondary></indexterm><para>Lets see how the <literal>Fraction</literal> class is declared:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Number subclass: #Fraction
   instanceVariableNames: 'numerator denominator'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Kernel-Numbers'
</screen>
<para>As expected there are two variables &#8211; named <firstterm>instance variables</firstterm>
&#8211; to define the <literal>numerator</literal> and <literal>denominator</literal> of
a fraction.  Each instance of fraction has its own numerator and its
own denominator.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>superclass</primary></indexterm>
<para>From this declaration, we observe there is a hierarchy in
the class definition: <literal>Fraction</literal> is a kind of
<literal>Number</literal>. This means a fraction inherits the internal state
(variables) and behavior (methods) defined in the <literal>Number</literal>
class. <literal>Fraction</literal> is called a <firstterm>subclass</firstterm> of <literal>Number</literal>,
and so naturally we call <literal>Number</literal> a <firstterm>superclass</firstterm> of <literal>Fraction</literal>.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary>inheritance</secondary></indexterm><para>A Class specifies the behavior of all of its instances.  It is useful
to be able to say <emphasis>this object is like that object, but with these
differences</emphasis>.  We do this in Smalltalk by having classes inherit instance
state and behavior from their parent Class.  This child, or subclass
then specifies just the instance state and behavior that is different
from its parent, retaining all the unmodified behaviours.
</para>
<para>This aspect of object-oriented programming is called
<firstterm>inheritance</firstterm>. In Cuis-Smalltalk, each class inherits from one parent
class.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>polymorphism</primary></indexterm>

<para>In Smalltalk, we say that each object decides for itself how it
responds to a message.  This is called <firstterm>polymorphism</firstterm>.  The same
message selector may be sent to objects of different Classes.  The
<emphasis>shape</emphasis> (morph) of the computation is different depending on the
specific class of the <emphasis>many</emphasis> (poly) possible classes of the
object receiving the message.
</para>
<para>Different kinds of objects respond to the same <literal>#printString</literal>
message in different, but appropriate ways.
</para>
<!-- instance creation -->
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>instance</primary><secondary>creation</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary>method</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>class method</secondary></indexterm><para>We have already met fractions. Those fractions are objects called
<firstterm>instance</firstterm>s of the class <literal>Fraction</literal>. To create an instance
we wrote <literal>5 / 4</literal>, the mechanism is based on message sending
and polymorphism.  Let us look into how this works.
</para>
<para>The number <literal>5</literal> is an integer receiving the message <literal>#/</literal>,
therefore looking at the method <literal>/</literal> in the <literal>Integer</literal>
class we can see how the fraction is instantiated. See part of this
method:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">/ aNumber
&quot;Refer to the comment in Number / &quot;
| quoRem |
aNumber isInteger ifTrue:
../..
   ifFalse: [^ (Fraction numerator: self denominator: aNumber) reduced]].
../..
</screen>
<para>From this source code, we learn that in some situations, the method
returns a fraction, reduced. We can expect that in some other
situation, an integer is returned, for example, <literal>6 / 2</literal>.
</para>
<para>In the example, we observe the message <literal>#numerator:denominator:</literal> is
sent to the class <literal>Fraction</literal>, such a message refers to a
<firstterm>class method</firstterm> understood only by the <literal>Fraction</literal> class. It
is expected such a named method returns an instance of a
<literal>Fraction</literal>.
</para>
<para>Try this out in a workspace:
</para><screen language="smalltalk">Fraction numerator: 24 denominator: 21
&#8658; 24/21
</screen>
<para>Observe how the resulting fraction is not reduced. Whereas it is reduced
when instantiated with the <literal>#/</literal> message:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">24 / 21
&#8658; 8/7
</screen>
<para>A class method is often used to create a new instance from a class. In
<link linkend="forLoop">forLoop</link>, the message <literal>#new</literal> is sent to the class
<literal>OrderedCollection</literal> to create a new empty collection;
<emphasis><literal>new</literal></emphasis> is a class method.
</para>
<para>In <link linkend="repeatLoop">repeatLoop</link>, the <literal>#newFrom:</literal> message is sent to the class
<literal>OrderedCollection</literal> to create a new collection filled with
elements from the array given in the argument; <emphasis><literal>newFrom:</literal></emphasis> is
another class method.
</para>
<!-- instance method -->
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>instance</primary><secondary>method</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>instance method</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>polymorphism</primary></indexterm>
<para>Now observe the hierarchy of the Number class:
</para>
<abstract><literal>Number</literal>
   <literal>Float</literal>
      <literal>BoxedFloat64</literal>
      <literal>SmallFloat64</literal>
   <literal>Fraction</literal>
   <literal>Integer</literal>
      <literal>LargePositiveInteger</literal>
         <literal>LargeNegativeInteger</literal>
      <literal>SmallInteger</literal>
</abstract>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>squared</literal></secondary></indexterm><para><literal>Float</literal>, <literal>Integer</literal> and <literal>Fraction</literal> are direct
descendants of the <literal>Number</literal> class. We have already learned about the
<literal>#squared</literal> message sent to integer and fraction instances:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">16 squared &#8658; 256
(2 / 3) squared &#8658; 4/9
</screen>
<para>As the <literal>#squared</literal> message is sent to <literal>Integer</literal> and
<literal>Fraction</literal> instances, the associated <literal>squared</literal> method is
called an <firstterm>instance method</firstterm>. This method is defined in both the
<literal>Number</literal> and <literal>Fraction</literal> classes.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>returned value (explicit)</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>returned value</primary></indexterm>
<para>Let&#8217;s examine this method in <literal>Number</literal>:
</para><screen language="smalltalk">Number&gt;&gt;squared
&quot;Answer the receiver multiplied by itself.&quot;
   ^ self * self
</screen>
<para>In an instance method source code, <literal>self</literal> refers to the
object itself, here it is the value of the number. The &#x2191; (also
<literal>^</literal>) symbol indicates to <emphasis>return</emphasis> the following value
<literal>self * self</literal>.  One might pronounce ^ as &#8220;return&#8221;.
</para>
<para>Now let&#8217;s examine this same method in <literal>Fraction</literal>:
</para><screen language="smalltalk">Fraction&gt;&gt;squared
   ^ Fraction
      numerator: numerator squared
      denominator: denominator squared
</screen>
<para>Here a new fraction is instantiated with the original instance
numerator and denominator being squared.
This alternate <literal>squared</literal> method, ensures a fraction instance is
returned.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>overriding</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>overriding</primary></indexterm>
<para>When the message <literal>#squared</literal> is sent to a number, different methods are
executed depending on if the number is a fraction or another kind of
number. Polymorphism means that the Class of each instance decides
how it will respond to a particular message.
Here, the <literal>Fraction</literal> class
is <firstterm>overriding</firstterm> the <literal>squared</literal> method, defined above in the
class hierarchy.  If a method is not overridden, an inherited method
is invoked to respond to the message.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>abs</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>Still in the <literal>Number</literal> hierarchy, let&#8217;s examine another example
of polymorphism with the <literal>#abs</literal> message:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">-10 abs &#8658; 10
5.3 abs &#8658; 5.3
(-5 / 3) abs &#8658; 5/3
</screen>
<para>The implementation in <literal>Number</literal> does not need much
explanation. There is the <literal>#ifTrue:ifFalse:</literal> we have not yet
discussed so far, but the code is quite self-explanatory:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Number&gt;&gt;abs
&quot;Answer a Number that is the absolute value (positive magnitude) of the 
receiver.&quot;
   self &lt; 0
      ifTrue: [^ self negated]
      ifFalse: [^ self]
</screen>
<para>This implementation will do just fine for the <literal>Number</literal>
subclasses. Nevertheless, there are several classes overriding it for
specialized or optimized cases.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>returned value (implicit)</secondary></indexterm><para>For example, regarding large positive integer, <literal>abs</literal> is
empty. Indeed, <emphasis role="bold">in the absence of explicitly returned value, the
default returned value is the instance itself</emphasis>, in our situation the
<literal>LargePositiveInteger</literal> instance:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">LargePositiveInteger&gt;&gt;abs
</screen>
<para>The <literal>LargeNegativeInteger</literal> knows it is negative and its absolute
value is itself but with its sign reversed, that is <literal>negated</literal>:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">LargeNegativeInteger&gt;&gt;abs
   ^ self negated
</screen>   
<para>These two overriding methods are more efficient as they avoid unnecessary
checks and ifTrue/ifFalse branches. Polymorphism is often used to avoid
unnecessary checks and code branches.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>keyboard shortcut</primary><secondary>implementors of (<userinput>Ctrl-m</userinput>)</secondary></indexterm>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
If you select the text <literal>abs</literal> in a Browser or
Workspace and right-click to get the context menu, you will find an
entry <command>Implementors of it</command>.  You can select this or use
<userinput>Ctrl-m</userinput> (<emphasis>i<emphasis role="bold">M</emphasis>plementors</emphasis>) to see how various methods for
<literal>#abs</literal> use polymorphism to specialize their answer to
produce the naturally expected result.
</para>
<para>As an object instance is modeled by its class, it is possible to
ask any object its
class with the <literal>#class</literal> message. Observe carefully the class
returned in lines 2 and 3:
</para>
<anchor id="askingClass"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">1 class &#8658; SmallInteger 
(1/3) class &#8658; Fraction 
(6/2) class &#8658; SmallInteger 
(1/3) asFloat class  &#8658; SmallFloat64 
(1.0/3) class &#8658; SmallFloat64 
'Hello' class &#8658; String 
('Hello' at: 1) class &#8658; Character
</screen>

</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Explore-OOP-from-the-Browser">
<title>Explore OOP from the Browser</title>
<!-- explain mini panel | instance | ? | class | -->
<para>In <link linkend="ch02_002dbrowserDetailed">ch02-browserDetailed</link> of the Browser, below the classes pane, there are three
buttons:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><command>instance</command>: to access the <emphasis role="bold">instance methods</emphasis> of
   the selected class. These methods apply to each and every instance
   of the class.  Each instance reacts to these.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>?</command>: to access to documentation &#8211; comment &#8211; of the
   selected class.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><command>class</command>: to access the <emphasis role="bold">class methods</emphasis> of the
   selected class. These methods are only accessible from the class
   itself.  Only the class object reacts to class methods.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>Below these three buttons, observe the wide text pane, which provides
contextual information on the selected item.
</para>
<para>Again, Class methods apply to the Class itself.  Instance Methods apply for 
all instances modeled by the class.  We saw above that
the class <literal>Fraction</literal>
has a method <literal>#numerator:denominator:</literal> which is used to get a new instance of
a <literal>Fraction</literal>.  There is only one <literal>Fraction</literal> class object.
Messages like <literal>#squared</literal> and <literal>#abs</literal> are sent to any <literal>Fraction</literal>
instance, of which there are many.
</para>
<para>Up to now, we have attempted to be very careful with definitions, but 
you know that when we say &#8220;a fraction&#8221; we
mean &#8220;an instance of the class <literal>Fraction</literal>&#8221;.
From here our language will be more casual.
</para>
<anchor id="floatInfo"/>
<para><emphasis>When the
<literal>Float</literal> class is selected, what is the information provided by
the text pane?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>We have spent much time here because it is important to avoid
confusion between instance methods and class
methods. Let&#8217;s consider the <literal>Float</literal> class as an example.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>class method</secondary></indexterm>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Class Methods.</emphasis> In <link linkend="ch03_002dfloatClassSide">ch03-floatClassSide</link> the methods listed are
class side, in the browser the <command>class</command> button is pressed to see this
list.
</para>
<anchor id="ch03_002dfloatClassSide"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch03-floatClassSide.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>From a Workspace, these methods are called with the message name sent
directly to the class:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Float e
&#8658; 2.718281828459045
Float epsilon
&#8658; 2.220446049250313e-16
Float fmax
&#8658; 1.7976931348623157e308
</screen>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>keyboard shortcut</primary><secondary>code completion (<userinput>tab</userinput>)</secondary></indexterm>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
You have noticed that text typed into the Workspace is
colored and highlighted based on what you type.  We will discuss this
below when we talk about the Smalltalk language, but the idea is to be
helpful.  If you start to type a word the Cuis Workspace knows about,
you can press the <userinput>tab</userinput> key and get a set of choices for
completion of the word.  Try typing <literal>Float epsi</literal> and
pressing <userinput>tab</userinput>.  You can then press <userinput>enter</userinput> and should see
<literal>Float epsilon</literal>.  Click elsewhere on the Workspace to make
this menu go away.
</para>
<para>Nevertheless, you can not send a class message to an instance of
<literal>Float</literal>, it throws an error and opens the red debugger
window. Just close the debug window for now to ignore the result.
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">3.14 pi
&#8658; MessageNotUnderstood: SmallFloat64&gt;&gt;pi
Float pi e
&#8658; MessageNotUnderstood: SmallFloat64&gt;&gt;e
</screen>
<para>Often these class methods are used to access constant values as seen in
the previous example or to create a new instance:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">OrderedCollection new
&#8658; Create a new empty ordered collection
Fraction numerator: 1 denominator: 3
&#8658; 1/3 &quot;a fraction instance&quot;
Float new
&#8658; 0.0
Float readFrom: '001.200'
&#8658; 1.2 
Integer primesUpTo: 20
&#8658; #(2 3 5 7 11 13 17 19) 
</screen>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>instance method</secondary></indexterm>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Instance methods.</emphasis> In <link linkend="ch03_002dfloatInstanceSide">ch03-floatInstanceSide</link>, the methods
listed are instance side, in the browser the <command>instance</command> button
is pressed to see this list.
</para>
<anchor id="ch03_002dfloatInstanceSide"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch03-floatInstanceSide.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>In a Workspace, these methods are called with the message name sent
directly to an instance:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">-10.12 abs &#8658; 10.12
3.14 cos &#8658; -0.9999987317275395
-10.12 * 2 &#8658; -20.24
</screen>
<para>Instance method messages cannot be sent directly to a class, you need
to instantiate an object first:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Float cos
&#8658; MessageNotUnderstood: Float class&gt;&gt;cos
Fraction squared
&#8658; MessageNotUnderstood: Fraction class&gt;&gt;squared
OrderedCollection add: 10
&#8658; MessageNotUnderstood: OrderedCollection class&gt;&gt;add:
</screen>
<para>Of course, you can mix both class and instance methods, as long as you
send the message to the appropriate class or instance:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Float pi cos
&#8658; -1.0
Float e ln
&#8658; 1.0 
(Fraction numerator: 4 denominator: 5) squared
&#8658; 16/25
OrderedCollection new add: Float pi; add: Float e; yourself
&#8658; an OrderedCollection(3.141592653589793 2.718281828459045) 

</screen>
<para>Here is another example from Spacewar! mixing class and instance
methods. This portion of code updates the orientation of a torpedo
according to its velocity vector:
</para>
<anchor id="torpedoOrientation"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">self rotation: (velocity y arcTan: velocity x) + Float halfPi
</screen>

<para>With this brief introduction to the system browser, you are now
equipped to explore the system classes.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Cuis-system-classes">
<title>Cuis system classes</title>
<para>As we noted above, Cuis-Smalltalk is a pure object-oriented environment. This 
means that every single entity you are dealing with is represented
as an instance of a class written in Cuis-Smalltalk itself. As a direct
consequence, Cuis-Smalltalk is mostly written in itself.  This means
the entire system is open to you to learn and play with.
</para>
<para>What we call system classes are models of fundamental objects. In
other programming languages, these would be implemented in
that language&#8217;s standard library.
</para>
<para>In a truly open system, there is no real distinction between system
classes and user classes, but it will help us to draw a boundary
around the most used objects. Let&#8217;s have a brief introduction to some
fundamental Smalltalk classes and their most important methods.
</para>
<para>In the upper left pane of the Browser, Categories of classes important
to start with are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Kernel-Numbers</emphasis>. Related to the different number
   representations and calculations, including mathematics functions,
   conversion, intervals, and even iterations.
</para>   
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Kernel-Text</emphasis>. Related to character and string as
   collection of characters.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Collections-Abstract</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Collections-Unordered</emphasis>,
   <emphasis role="bold">Collections-Sequenceable</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Collections-Arrayed</emphasis>.
   Related to Array, Dictionary, Set, OrderedCollection and many more.
   This category includes common accessing, enumeration, mathematical
   functions, and sorting.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Kernel_002dNumbers">
<title>Kernel-Numbers</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>category</secondary></indexterm>
<para>The top hierarchy <literal>Number</literal> class shows most of the behaviors
inherited by the subclasses as <literal>Float</literal>, <literal>Integer</literal> and
<literal>Fraction</literal>. The Smalltalk way to learn about a behavior is to
point the System Browser toward a top hierarchy class and explore
the method categories.
</para>
<para>Let&#8217;s suppose we want to round a float number. In <literal>Number</literal>, we
explore the <emphasis role="bold">Truncation and round off</emphasis> method category to
discover several behaviors. The next thing to do is to test these
messages in a Workspace to discover the one we are searching for:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>roundTo:</literal></secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>roundUpTo:</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<anchor id="roundingNumbers"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">1.264 roundTo: 0.1 &#8658; 1.3 
1.264 roundTo: 0.01 &#8658; 1.26 
1.264 roundUpTo: 0.01 &#8658; 1.27
1.264 roundTo: 0.001 &#8658; 1.264
</screen>


<indexterm role="cp"><primary>loop</primary><secondary>for</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>loop</primary><secondary>for</secondary><tertiary>step</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>for loop</primary><see>loop</see></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>to:do:</literal></secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>to:do:by</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<para>Number is a very strange place to look for an indexed loop in a given
interval. Nevertheless, an interval is defined by start and stop
numbers. In the <literal>Number</literal> class, the method category
<emphasis role="bold">intervals</emphasis> reveals related behaviors. These methods work
polymorphically with most kinds of numbers:
</para>
<anchor id="intervalLoops"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">1 to: 10 do: [:i | Transcript show: 1 / i; space]
&#8658; 1 (1/2) (1/3) (1/4) (1/5) (1/6) (1/7) (1/8) (1/9) (1/10)

1 to: 10 by: 2 do: [:i | Transcript show: 1 / i; space]
&#8658; 1 (1/3) (1/5) (1/7) (1/9)

1/10 to: 5/3 by: 1/2 do: [:i | Transcript show: i; space]
&#8658; (1/10) (3/5) (11/10) (8/5) (1/10) (3/5) (11/10) (8/5) 

Float pi to: 5 by: 1/3 do: [:i | Transcript show: i; space]
&#8658; 3.141592653589793 3.4749259869231266 3.80825932025646
4.141592653589793 4.474925986923126 4.808259320256459
</screen>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>loop</primary><secondary>repeat</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>repeat</primary><see>loop</see></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>integer</secondary><tertiary><literal>timesRepeat:</literal></tertiary></indexterm>
<para>Now, in the <literal>Integer</literal> class, explore the method category
<command>enumerating</command>, to find <literal>timesRepeat:</literal>. When a
portion of code needs to be executed several times
<footnote><para>More strictly, to be repeated an integer number of times.</para></footnote>, without
the need for an index, the <literal>#timesRepeat:</literal> message is sent to an
integer. We already saw this variant in a previous section of this
chapter.  Throwing a 6-face die 5 times can be simulated with
an integer:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>integer</secondary><tertiary><literal>atRandom</literal></tertiary></indexterm><anchor id="playingDice"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">5 timesRepeat: [Transcript show: 6 atRandom; space]
&#8658; 1 2 4 6 2
</screen>

<para>Note: Expect a different result each time.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary><literal>Interval</literal></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>interval</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>to:</literal></secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary><literal>to:by:</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<para>Intervals of numbers can be defined on their own, for future use:
</para>
<anchor id="interval"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">1 to: 10
&#8658; (1 to: 10)

1 to: 10 by: 2
&#8658; (1 to: 9 by: 2)
</screen>

<para>Intervals work with other kinds of objects such as <literal>Character</literal>s:
</para><screen language="smalltalk">$d to: $h
&#8658; #($d $e $f $g $h)
</screen>
<para>In fact, an interval is an object of its own. It is a sort of
collection:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">(1 to: 10) class
&#8658; Interval

(1 to: 10 by: 2) squared
&#8658; #(1 9 25 49 81)

(1 to: 10) atRandom
&#8658; 4 &quot;different result each time&quot;
</screen>
<para>In Spacewar!, when a ship is destroyed it is teleported to a random
position in the square gameplay area. Intervals are handy to pick 
random coordinates. In the example below, the variable
<literal>randomCoordinate</literal> holds a block of code &#8211; called an anonymous
function in other languages. It picks a random value in the
interval consisting of the gameplay area&#8217;s left and right extents:
</para>
<anchor id="teleportShipInterval"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">randomCoordinate := [(area left to: area right) atRandom].
aShip
   velocity: 0 @ 0;
   morphPosition: randomCoordinate value @ randomCoordinate value
</screen>


<anchor id="cosTable"/>
<para><emphasis>Compute the cosine values in
the interval [0 ; 2PI]&#44; each 1/10. Output the result in the transcript.</emphasis>
</para>


<!-- Integer bits representation and manipulation -->
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>integer</secondary><tertiary>base</tertiary></indexterm><para>Integer numbers are represented in different bases when prefixed with
the base and &#8220;r&#8221;. The <command>r</command> stands for radix, the base root by
which the following number is interpreted.
When executing and printing <userinput>Ctrl-p</userinput> on such a
number, it is immediately printed in the decimal base:
</para>
<anchor id="integerBase"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">2r1111 &#8658; 15
16rF &#8658; 15
8r17 &#8658; 15
20rF &#8658; 15
10r15 &#8658; 15
</screen>

<para>Writing numbers as Mayans or Babylonians<footnote><para>Base 20 and 60
number representations are not exclusive to these civilisations,
although they are the most documented use cases.</para></footnote>:
</para>
<anchor id="countingAncients"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">&quot;The Babylonians&quot;
60r10 &#8658; 60
60r30 &#8658; 180
60r60 &#8658; 360
60r30 + 60r60 &#8658; 540 
(60r30 + 60r60) printStringRadix: 60 &#8658; '60r90' 

&quot;The Mayans&quot;
20r10 &#8658; 20
20r40 &#8658; 80 &quot;pronounced 4-twenties in some languages&quot;
20r100 &#8658; 400
</screen>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>bits shifting</primary></indexterm>
<para>Because of the nature of a number represented in base 2, shifting its
bits left and right is equivalent to multiplying by 2 and dividing by
2:
</para>
<anchor id="shiftBits"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">(2r1111 &lt;&lt; 1) printStringBase: 2 &#8658; '11110'
2r1111 &lt;&lt; 1 &#8658; 30
(2r1111 &gt;&gt; 1) printStringBase: 2 &#8658; '111'
2r1111 &gt;&gt; 1 &#8658; 7
</screen>

<anchor id="multiplyBy1024"/>
<para><emphasis>How would you multiply
the integer 360 by 1024&#44; without using the multiplication operation?</emphasis>
</para>



<bridgehead renderas="sect2">Hiatus with decimal numbers</bridgehead>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>decimal</secondary></indexterm>
<para>We saw decimal numbers are written with a dot &#8220;.&#8221; to separate the
integer and the decimal parts: <literal>1.5</literal>, <literal>1235.021</literal>
or <literal>0.5</literal>. The number <literal>0.0000241</literal> is more easily
written with the scientific notation <literal>2.41e-5</literal>; it means 2
preceded by 5 zeros or 2 as the fifth digit after the decimal dot.
</para>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
Computers encode and store decimal numbers imprecisely. You
need to be aware of that when doing computation and equality
comparisons. Many systems hide these errors because they are very tiny
errors. Cuis-Smalltalk does not hide this inaccuracy.  There is good
information about this in the class comment of <literal>Float</literal>.
</para>
<anchor id="FloatPrecision"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">0.1 + 0.2 - 0.3
&#8658; 5.551115123125783e-17
</screen>

<para>In <link linkend="FloatPrecision">FloatPrecision</link>, the returned value should be zero but it is
not the case. The computer returns <literal>5.55e-17</literal>, or
<literal>0.0000000000000000555</literal>, it is very close to zero, but there
is an error.
</para>
<anchor id="exeFloatPrecision"/>
<para><emphasis>Give 3 calculations showing errors compared
to the expected results.</emphasis>
</para>


<para>When accuracy is mandatory use the Rational Numbers
representation in Cuis-Smalltalk.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>rational (fraction)</secondary></indexterm>
<para>A rational number is written with the division symbol between two
integers: do <userinput>Ctrl-p</userinput> on <literal>5/2</literal> &#8658;
<literal>5/2</literal>. Cuis-Smalltalk returns a rational number, it does not compute a
decimal.
</para>
<anchor id="exeZeroDivide"/>
<para><emphasis>What happens when
executing this code</emphasis> <literal>5/0</literal><emphasis>?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>Let&#8217;s come back to our computer&#8217;s dyscalculia with decimal numbers. When
using the rational numbers, the <link linkend="FloatPrecision">FloatPrecision</link> becomes:
</para>
<anchor id="FractionPrecision"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">(1/10) + (2/10) - (3/10)
&#8658; 0
</screen>

<para>This time we have the expected result. Under the covers, the computer
only does the calculations with integer components so no roundoff
results. This is a fine example where solving some problems requires a
paradigm shift.
</para>
<anchor id="exeFractionPrecision"/>
<para><emphasis>Return to
<link linkend="exeFloatPrecision">exeFloatPrecision</link> and use rational numbers to represent decimal
numbers. The errors will be resolved.</emphasis>
</para>


<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>conversion</secondary></indexterm><para>Cuis-Smalltalk knows how to convert a decimal number to a fraction, by
sending the message <literal>#asFraction</literal>. We already acknowledged the
computer&#8217;s dyscalculia with decimal numbers, this is why when
asking for a fraction representation we have this strange answer. The
internal computer representation of <literal>1.3</literal> is not exactly as
it seems:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">(13/10) asFloat
&#8658; 1.3

(13/10) asFloat asFraction
&#8658; 5854679515581645/45035996273704
</screen>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Kernel_002dText">
<title>Kernel-Text</title>
<para>Notably, this category contains classes <literal>Character</literal>, <literal>String</literal> and <literal>Symbol</literal>. <literal>String</literal> instances are collections of <literal>Character</literal> instances. All these are limited to the small <acronym>ASCII</acronym> character set. The corresponding classes that can handle the much larger Unicode character set are <literal>UnicodeCodePoint</literal>, <literal>UnicodeString</literal>, and <literal>UnicodeSymbol</literal>. As stated before, the Unicode classes can also handle <acronym>ASCII</acronym>, and they are interchangeable. You usually don&#8217;t need to care about which flavor (<acronym>ASCII</acronym> or Unicode) an instance actually is.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>character</primary></indexterm>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Character/UnicodeCodePoint.</emphasis> An individual character is written prefixed with a &#8220;$&#8221;, for example: <literal>$A</literal> or <literal>$φ</literal>. It can be defined with the class side method <literal>codePoint:</literal>. Note, however, that you can ask Character only about valid Characters. It is generally safer to ask UnicodeCodePoint instead:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">Character codePoint: 65 &#8658; $A
Character codePoint: 966 &#8658; nil
UnicodeCodePoint codePoint: 966 &#8658; $φ
</screen>
<para>There are class-side methods for nonprintable characters:
<literal>Character tab</literal>, <literal>Character lf</literal>, etc.
</para>
<para>Additionally, <literal>UnicodeCodePoint</literal> defines a <literal>#namedCharactersMap</literal>, that lets you enter many Unicode characters easily, like:
</para>
<para><literal>\leftright</literal> then press spacebar.
</para>
<para>As each string is a collection of characters, when iterating a string we
can use the <literal>Character</literal> instance methods:
</para>
<anchor id="apples12"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">'There are 12 apples.' select: [:c |c isDigit].
&#8658; '12'
</screen>

<anchor id="selectApples"/>
<para><emphasis>Modify <link linkend="apples12">apples12</link> to
reject the numeric characters.</emphasis>
</para>


<indexterm role="cp"><primary>method</primary><secondary>category</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>string</primary></indexterm>
<para><emphasis role="bold">String.</emphasis> <literal>String</literal> is a very large class, it comes with
more than 200 methods. It is useful to browse these method categories
to see common ways to group methods.
</para>
<para>Sometimes you may not see a category related to what you&#8217;re looking for right away.
</para>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
If you expect a method selector to start with a specific letter,
click-select the <command>-- all --</command> method category, then move the
cursor over the pane listing the method names.  Press this character,
e.g. <literal>$f</literal>.  This will scroll the method pane to the first
method name starting with an &#8220;f&#8221;.
</para>
<para>Consider the case where you need to search for a substring, a string within a
string: when browsing
the <literal>String</literal> class, search for method categories named like
<emphasis role="bold">finding...</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">accessing</emphasis>. There you find a family of
<literal>findXXX</literal> methods. Read the comments at the beginning of these
methods:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">findString: subString
   &quot;Answer the index of subString within the receiver, starting at
   start. If the receiver does not contain subString, answer 0.&quot;
   ^ self findString: subString startingAt: 1.
</screen>
<para>Or:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">findString: key startingAt: start caseSensitive: caseSensitive
   &quot;Answer the index in this String at which the substring key first
   occurs, at or beyond start.  The match can be case-sensitive or
   not.  If no match is found, zero will be returned.&quot;
   ../..
</screen>
<para>Then experiment with the potentially interesting messages in a workspace:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">'I love apples' findString: 'love' &#8658; 3 &quot;match starts at position 3&quot;
'I love apples' findString: 'hate'
&#8658;  0 &quot;not found&quot;
'We humans, we all love apples' findString: 'we'
&#8658; 12 
'We humans, we all love apples'
   findString: 'we'
   startingAt: 1
   caseSensitive: false
&#8658; 1 
'we humans, we all love apples' findString: 'we'
&#8658; 1 
'we humans, we all love apples' findString: 'we' startingAt: 2
&#8658; 12
</screen>
<para>Following these paths will, most of the time, lead you toward the answer
you are looking for.
</para>
<!-- an exercise to find a method given a behavior -->
<anchor id="formatString"/>
<para><emphasis>We want to format a
string of the form &#8217;Joe bought XX apples and YY oranges&#8217; to the form
&#8217;Joe bought 5 apples and 4 oranges&#8217;. What message should be used?</emphasis>
</para>


</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Spacewar_0021-States-and-Behaviors">
<title>Spacewar! States and Behaviors</title>

<sect2 label="">
<title>The game states</title>
<para>After defining the classes involved in the game design, we now define
 several states of these classes:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A <literal>SpaceWar</literal> instance representing the gameplay needs to
 know about the <literal>centralStar</literal>, the <literal>ships</literal>, the
 fired <literal>torpedoes</literal>, and its <literal>color</literal>.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A <literal>CentralStar</literal> has a <literal>mass</literal> state. It is
 necessary to compute the gravity force applied to a given ship.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A <literal>SpaceShip</literal> instance knows about its <literal>name</literal>,
 its <literal>position</literal> coordinates, its <literal>heading</literal> angle,
 its <literal>velocity</literal> vector, its <literal>fuel</literal> gauge, its
 count of the available <literal>torpedoes</literal>, its <literal>mass</literal>
 and its <literal>acceleration</literal> engine boost.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>A <literal>Torpedo</literal> has <literal>position</literal>,
 <literal>velocity</literal> and <literal>lifeSpan</literal> states.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>We need to explain the mathematical nature of these states, and then
discuss their object representation in the instance variables of our
classes.
</para>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
In the following sections, to ease reading we will write
&#8220;the variable <literal>myVar</literal> is a <literal>String</literal>&#8221; instead of the
correct but cumbersome &#8220;the instance variable <literal>myVar</literal> is a
reference to a <literal>String</literal> instance&#8221;.
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect1"><literal>SpaceWar</literal></bridgehead>
<para>This object is the entry into the game. We want a meaningful class
name. Its instance variables are the involved protagonists of the
game:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>centralStar</literal> is the unique <literal>CentralStar</literal> of
  the game play. We need to know about it to request its mass.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>ships</literal> is a collection of the two player ships. It
  is an <literal>Array</literal> instance, its size is fixed to two elements.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>torpedoes</literal> is a collection of the fired torpedoes
  in the gameplay. As this quantity is variable, a dynamic
  <literal>OrderedCollection</literal> makes sense.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<bridgehead renderas="sect1"><literal>CentralStar</literal></bridgehead>

<para>Its unique instance variable, <literal>mass</literal>, is a number, most likely
an <literal>Integer</literal>.
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect1"><literal>SpaceShip</literal></bridgehead>

<para>The spaceship is the most complex object, some clarifications
regarding its variables are needed.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>name</literal> is a <literal>String</literal>.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary><literal>Point</literal></primary></indexterm>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>coordinates</primary></indexterm>

</listitem><listitem><para><literal>position</literal> is a 2D screen coordinate, a
  location. Smalltalk uses the <literal>Point</literal> class to represent
  such objects. It understands many mathematics operations as
  operations on vectors; very useful for mechanical calculations.
</para>
<para>A point is easily instantiated with the binary message <literal>#@</literal> send
  to a number with another number as its argument: <literal>100 @
  200</literal> returns a <literal>Point</literal> instance representing the
  coordinates (x;y) = (100;200).
</para>
<para>The ship&#8217;s <literal>position</literal> is regularly recomputed according to
  the law of the Galilean reference frame. The computation depends on
  the ship&#8217;s velocity, it&#8217;s current engine boost, and the gravity pull
  of the central star.
</para> 
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>heading</literal> is an angle in radians, the direction
  where the ship&#8217;s nose is pointing.  It is therefore a <literal>Float</literal>
  number. At the game&#8217;s start, the ships are oriented to the top, the
  <literal>heading</literal> value is then -pi/2 radians; the oy axis is
  oriented from the top to the bottom of the screen.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>velocity</literal> is the vector representing the
  instantaneous speed of the ship. It is a <literal>Point</literal> instance.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>fuel</literal> is the gauge, as long as it is not zero, the
  player can ignite the ship&#8217;s rocket engine to provide acceleration to move
  around and to counter the central star&#8217;s gravity pull. It is an
  integer number.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>torpedoes</literal> is the quantity of available torpedoes
  the player can fire. It is an <literal>Integer</literal> number.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>mass</literal> is an <literal>Integer</literal> representing the ship
  mass.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>acceleration</literal> is the intrinsic ship acceleration
  norm provided when the ship&#8217;s rockets are ignited. It is therefore
  an <literal>Integer</literal> number.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>A few words regarding the Euclidean coordinates: the origin of our
orthonormal frame is the central star, its first vector is oriented
toward the right of the screen, and the second one towards the top of
the screen. This choice eases the computation of the ship&#8217;s acceleration,
velocity and position.  More on this below.
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect1"><literal>Torpedo</literal></bridgehead>
<para>A torpedo is launched or &#8220;fired&#8221; from a ship with an initial
velocity related to the ship&#8217;s velocity. Once the torpedo life span
counter reaches zero, it self-destructs.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>position</literal> is a 2D screen coordinate, a
  <literal>Point</literal> instance. Unlike the ship, it does not accelerate based
  on the gravity pull of the central star. Indeed, a torpedo does not
  come with a mass state.  For our purposes, it is essentially
  zero. Its position over time only depends on the torpedo velocity
  and its initial acceleration.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>heading</literal> is an angle in radians, the direction
  where the torpedo nose is pointing. Its value matches the ship
  heading when fired, it is therefore a <literal>Float</literal> number too.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>velocity</literal> is a vector representing the
  instantaneous speed of the torpedo. It is constant over the torpedo&#8217;s
  lifespan. Again velocity is kept as a <literal>Point</literal> instance.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>lifeSpan</literal> is an integer number counter, when it
  reaches zero the torpedo self-destructs.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Instance variables</title>
<!-- show on one class declaration how to put the variable -->
<para>In the previous chapter, we explained how to define the four classes
<literal>SpaceWar</literal>, <literal>CentralStar</literal>, <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and
<literal>Torpedo</literal>. In this section, we will add to these definitions
the instance variables &#8211; states &#8211; discussed above.
</para>
<para>To add the variables to the <literal>Torpedo</literal> class, from the Browser,
select this class. Next, add the variable names to the
<literal>instanceVariableNames:</literal> keyword, separated by one space
character. Finally, save the updated class definition with
<userinput>Ctrl-s</userinput> shortcut:
</para>
<anchor id="torpedoClassVariables"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">Object subclass: #Torpedo
   instanceVariableNames: 'position heading velocity lifeSpan'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'
</screen>

<anchor id="spacewarVar"/>
<para><emphasis>Add the instance variables we discussed earlier to the
<literal>SpaceWar</literal>, <literal>CentralStar</literal> and <literal>SpaceShip</literal> classes.</emphasis>
</para>



</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Behaviors</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>message</primary><secondary>setter</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>message</primary><secondary>getter</secondary></indexterm><para>Some of these states need to be accessed from other entities:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>When initializing a spaceship, we want to set its name
  with a keyword message categorised as a <firstterm>setter</firstterm>:
  <literal>ship name: 'The needle'</literal>.
</para>  
</listitem><listitem><para>To compute the gravity force applied to an object owning a
  mass, we want to get its value with a unary message categorised as
  a <firstterm>getter</firstterm>: <literal>star mass * ship mass</literal>.
</para>  
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>To write these behaviors in the Browser, first select the class then
the method category you want &#8211; when none, select <command>-- all
--</command>.
</para>
<para>In the code pane below appears a method template:
</para>
<anchor id="methodTemplate"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">messageSelectorAndArgumentNames
   &quot;comment stating purpose of message&quot;
   | temporary variable names |
   statements
</screen>

<para>It describes itself as:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Line 1.</emphasis> It is a mandatory method name, the same as
   the message.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Line 2.</emphasis> An optional comment surrounded by double
   quote.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Line 3.</emphasis> An optional list of variables local to the
   method, surrounded by pipe characters.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Line 4.</emphasis> A subsequent list of message sendings and
   assignments.
</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>
<para>The getter <literal>mass</literal> on <literal>SpaceShip</literal> is written as:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">SpaceShip&gt;&gt;mass
   ^ mass
</screen>
<para>The <literal>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;</literal> part is not valid code and should not be
written in the Browser. It is a text convention to inform the reader
the subsequent method is from the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> class.
</para>
<anchor id="spaceShipGetters"/>
<para><emphasis>Write the
<literal>SpaceShip</literal> getter messages for its
<literal>position</literal>&#44; <literal>velocity</literal> and <literal>mass</literal>
attributes.</emphasis>
</para>


<indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>assignment</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>:=</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>&#x2190;</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Some instance variables need to be set from another entity,
so a <firstterm>setter</firstterm> keyword message is necessary.
To set the name of a space ship we add the
following method:
</para>
<screen language="smalltalk">SpaceShip&gt;&gt;name: aString
   name := aString
</screen>
<para>The := character is an assignment, it means the
<literal>name</literal> instance variable is bound to the <literal>aString</literal>
object. 
To type in this symbol type <keycap>_</keycap> then space,
Cuis-Smalltalk will turn it into the left arrow symbol.  Alternatively write
<literal>name := aString</literal>.  One might pronounce := as &#8220;gets&#8221;.
</para>
<para>Since <literal>name</literal> is an instance variable, each instance method
knows to use the box for the name.  The meaning here is that we are
placing the value of the <literal>aString</literal> argument into the
instance&#8217;s box called <literal>name</literal>.
</para>
<para>Since each instance variable box can hold an object of any class, we
like to name the argument to show that we intend that the
<literal>name</literal> variable should hold a string, an instance of the
<literal>String</literal> class.
</para>
<anchor id="spaceShipSetters"/>
<para><emphasis>Ship <literal>position</literal> and <literal>velocity</literal>, as well as
torpedo <literal>heading</literal> will need to be set at game start-up or
when a ship jumps in hyperspace.  Write the appropriate setters.</emphasis>
</para>


<para>Observe how we do not have a setter message for the spaceship
<literal>mass</literal> attribute. Indeed, it does not make sense to change
the mass of a ship from another object. In fact, if we consider both
player ships to be of equal mass, we should remove the <literal>mass</literal>
variable and edit the <literal>mass</literal> method to return a literal number:
</para>
<anchor id="methodConstant"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">SpaceShip&gt;&gt;mass
   ^ 1
</screen>

<para>On the other hand, we could also consider the <literal>mass</literal> to
depend on the consumed fuel and torpedoes. After all, 93&#160;% of
Saturn&#160;V rocket&#8217;s mass was made up of its fuel. We will discuss
more about that later in the <link linkend="artRefactoring">chapter about
refactoring</link>.
</para>

<anchor id="simpleControls"/><bridgehead renderas="sect3">Controls</bridgehead>
<para>A spaceship controlled by the player understands messages to adjust
its direction and acceleration<footnote><para>The velocity is a consequence
of the accelerations applied to the spaceship.</para></footnote>:
</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Direction.</emphasis> The ship&#8217;s heading is controlled with the
  <literal>#left</literal> and <literal>#right</literal> messages. The former decrements the
  <literal>heading</literal> by 0.1 and the latter increments it by 0.1.
</para>
<anchor id="shipHeading"/>
<para><emphasis>Write
  two methods named <literal>left</literal> and <literal>right</literal> to shift the ship
  heading of 0.1 according to the indications above.</emphasis>
</para>


<para><emphasis role="bold">Acceleration.</emphasis> When the <literal>#push</literal> message is sent to
  the ship, the engines are ignited, and an internal acceleration of 10
  units of acceleration are applied to the ship. When the <literal>#unpush</literal>
  message is sent, the acceleration stops.
</para>
<anchor id="shipAcceleration"/>
<para><emphasis>Write two methods named <literal>push</literal> and <literal>unpush</literal> to
  adjust the ship&#8217;s inner acceleration according to the indications
  above.</emphasis>
</para>



</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Initializing</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary><literal>initialize</literal></primary></indexterm>
<para>When an instance is created, for example, <literal>SpaceShip new</literal>, it
is automatically initialized: the message <literal>#initialize</literal> is sent to
the newly created object and its matching <literal>initialize</literal> instance
side method is called.
</para>
<para>The initializing process is useful to set the default values of the
instance variables. When we create a new space ship object we want to
set its default position, speed, and acceleration:
</para>
<anchor id="initSpaceShip"/>
<screen language="smalltalk">SpaceShip&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   velocity := 0 @ 0.
   position := 100 @ 100.
   acceleration := 0
</screen>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary><literal>super</literal></primary></indexterm>
<para>In the method <link linkend="initSpaceShip">initSpaceShip</link>, observe the first line
<literal>super initialize</literal>. When a message is sent to
<literal>super</literal>, it refers to the superclass of the class&#8217;s method
using <literal>super</literal>. So far, the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> parent class is
<literal>Object</literal>, therefore the <literal>Object&gt;&gt;initialize</literal> method is
called first for initialization.
</para>
<para>When created, a spaceship is positioned to the top and right of the
central star. It has no velocity nor internal acceleration &#8211; only the
gravity pull of the central star.  Its nose points in direction of the
top of the game display.
</para>
<para>You probably noticed there is no code to initialize the
<literal>heading</literal>, something like <literal>heading := Float
halfPi negated</literal> to orient the ship in the direction of the top of the
screen. The truth is we don&#8217;t need the <literal>heading</literal> attribute,
this information will be provided by the class <literal>Morph</literal> used
later as a parent class of <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal>.  At
this time, the <literal>heading</literal> variable will be removed and we
will define the heading behavior with the appropriate <literal>heading</literal>
and <literal>heading:</literal> methods.
</para>
<anchor id="initCentralStar"/>
<para><emphasis>Write the
method to initialize the central star with 8000 units of mass.</emphasis>
</para>

<!-- -->
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
