<chapter label="" id="Visual-with-Morph">
<title>Visual with Morph</title>

<blockquote><attribution>John   Maloney</attribution>
<para>Morphic is a user interface framework that makes it easy and fun to
build lively interactive user interfaces.
</para></blockquote>





<para>What would we expect if we asked for good support for building GUIs in a
programming system?
</para>
<para>All modern computers (and phones, etc) have high resolution color
displays. Any software running on them, that is accessible to a user,
needs to show stuff on that Display.
</para>
<para>Conventional UI managers (that is, Operating Systems and Web Browsers)
started by including only the most basic GUI elements first: basic
text editors, buttons, simple lists, scrolling for large content, and
(usually) multiple resizeable overlapping windows. Anything else needs
to be handled via additional libraries. While there are libraries for
handling richer content (D3.js and Matplotlib are examples), the
result is not consistent, neither for developers nor for users.
</para>
<para>Cuis-Smalltalk takes a different approach, pioneered by Smalltalk-80 and
especially Self. We will get into detail in the next chapter,
<emphasis>The Fundamentals of Morph</emphasis>.  For now, let&#8217;s deal with Morphs directly.
</para>
<para>We take the high quality Display for granted, as well as a mouse, finger or
other pointing device. And we build on the objective of providing
ample possibilities for GUIs both in existing, and in novel styles and
designs yet to be invented. Additionally, in the usual Smalltalk way,
all the framework code is available for study and modification. There
are no third party libraries. Only the lowest level code is
precompiled, but that still can be overriden or changed.
</para>
<para>Therefore every object you see in Cuis-Smalltalk is a <literal>Morph</literal> or is
composed of <literal>Morph</literal>s.  Basically, a <literal>Morph</literal> is an object
with state and behavior that can also depict itself on a computer
display screen.
</para>
<para>Because Morphs are useful, when you look at
class <literal>Morph</literal> in a Hierarchy Browser you will
see a large number of methods and many, many subclasses.
But the basic ideas are quite simple.
</para>



<sect1 label="" id="Installing-a-Package">
<title>Installing a Package</title>
<para>This chapter will require you to install the package
<command>UI-Shapes.pck.st</command>, it is part of the
<ulink url="https://github.com/Cuis-Smalltalk/Cuis-Smalltalk-UI">Cuis-Smalltalk-UI</ulink>
project. To fetch this package from the web, you have two options:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Grab the file
  <filename><ulink url="https://github.com/Cuis-Smalltalk/Cuis-Smalltalk-UI/raw/main/tools/UI-Shapes.pck.st">UI-Shapes.pck.st</ulink></filename>
  and save it in the same folder as your Cuis-Smalltalk image file.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>In the Cuis-Smalltalk image folder, clone its Git repository:
</para>
<screen>git clone git@github.com:Cuis-Smalltalk/Cuis-Smalltalk-UI.git
</screen>
<para>Along the <command>UI-Shapes.pck.st</command> packages there are other ones
you can also discover in this repository.
</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>package</primary><secondary>load</secondary><tertiary>by code</tertiary></indexterm><para>Once done, in a Workspace execute the code to install the package:
</para>
<screen>Feature require: 'UI-Shapes'
</screen>
<para>Your Cuis-Smalltalk environment is now equiped for the next sections of this
chapter.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Ellipse-Morph">
<title>Ellipse Morph</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>ellipse</secondary></indexterm><para>Let&#8217;s start with one of the basic morphs, an <literal>EllipseMorph</literal>.
You could write <literal>EllipseMorph new openInWorld</literal> and
<command><emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>o-it</command>, but we are doing visual things for now, so let&#8217;s
get a World Menu and select from <command>New Morph...</command> <command>Basic</command>
submenu and drag onto the desktop.
</para>
<para>Every time one obtains a morph from a <command>New Morph...</command> submenu,
one gets a different morph but made to a standard style.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d01_002dEllipseMorphFromMenu"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-01-EllipseMorphFromMenu.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>The basic challenge of <firstterm>user interface design</firstterm> is
to communicate visibility and control.
Where am I?  What can I do here?
</para>
<para>One of the balance points in design is how to eliminate clutter.  One
useful strategy is to reveal capabilities in context as they are
needed.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>halo</secondary></indexterm><para>In the case of Cuis-Smalltalk, you have to know some basics because helpful
tools are there but stay out of the way.  At any time you can
<userinput>Right-Click</userinput> on the desktop to get the World Menu.  You can also
<userinput>Middle-Click</userinput> on any <literal>Morph</literal> to get a <firstterm>halo</firstterm> of
<firstterm>construction handles</firstterm>, which show up as small colored circular
icons.  If you pause the cursor over one of these, you get a <firstterm>tool
tip</firstterm>, a temporary text popup who&#8217;s name should give a clue to its
usage.
</para>
<para>If you click elsewhere the construction handles leave, but you can get them
back at any time with a mouse click.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d03_002dDragToEnlarge"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-03-DragToEnlarge.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Now that you know this, move the yellow lower right handle with tool
tip <command>Change size</command> via <firstterm>Click-Drag</firstterm>.  Just hold down the
left mouse button while the cursor is over the handle, move the cursor
to the right and down, and release the mouse button.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d04_002dEnlarged"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-04-Enlarged.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Submorph">
<title>Submorph</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>submorph</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>rectangle</secondary></indexterm><para>Morphs can contain other morphs.  These interior morphs are called
<firstterm>submorph</firstterm>s of their containing morph. Again, you can do this by
writing the software &#8220;code&#8221;, but let&#8217;s do it directly with a
<literal>BoxedMorph</literal>.
</para>
<para>First we obtain a <literal>BoxedMorph</literal> from the <command>New morph...</command>
submenus. The <literal>BoxedMorph</literal> instance displays itself as a
rect with a border.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d05_002dAddRectangle"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-05-AddRectangle.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Now drag the rect over the ellipse and <userinput>Middle-Click</userinput> on the
rect and click on the blue construction handle to gets the rect&#8217;s
<firstterm>Morph Menu</firstterm>.  Use the menu selection <command>embed into</command> and
select the ellipse as its new parent.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d06_002dEmbedRectIntoEllipse"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-06-EmbedRectIntoEllipse.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Now when you click-drag the ellipse, or use the <command>Pick up</command> or
<command>Move</command> construction handles, the rect is just a decoration for
the ellipse.
</para>
<para>Indeed, the rect seems to have fused into the ellipse.  Using the
mouse where the rect shows itself is just using the mouse on the
ellipse.  This rect does not have many interesting behaviors.
</para>
<para>Let&#8217;s add a behavior to just this one <literal>BoxedMorph</literal>.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="A-brief-introduction-to-Inspectors">
<title>A brief introduction to Inspectors</title>
<para>To get the construction halo for an interior morph, just
<userinput>Middle-Click</userinput> multiple times to &#8220;drill down&#8221; through the
submorph hierarchy.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d07_002dMiddleClickRect"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-07-MiddleClickRect.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<anchor id="ch06_002d08_002d2ndMidClckToSubmorph"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-08-2ndMidClckToSubmorph.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>There is an orange handle on the right, just under the green
<command>Duplicate</command> handle.  <userinput>Left-Click</userinput> this to get the
<command>Debug</command> menu.  Use this menu to get an <firstterm>Inspector</firstterm> for the
rect.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>tools</primary><secondary>inspector</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>inspector</primary><see>tools</see></indexterm>
<para>Observe <link linkend="ch06_002d11aColorClickOnRect">ch06-11aColorClickOnRect</link>, on the left we have a pane for
self, all inst vars, and the individual instance variables.  Clicking
to select &#8220;all inst vars&#8221; and the values pane on the right shows
that the owner of the rect is the ellipse and rect currently has no
submorphs.
</para>
<para>The lower pane is a Smalltalk code editor, basically a workspace,
where <literal>self</literal> is bound to the object we are inspecting.
</para>
<para>Inspectors work for every object by the way, not just morphs.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d11aColorClickOnRect"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-11aColorClickOnRect.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>To add a behavior to all instances of a class, we create an instance
method.  Here we are going to create a behavior for &#8220;just this one
<literal>BoxedMorph</literal> instance&#8221;.
</para>
<anchor id="morphProperties"/><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>properties</secondary></indexterm><para>In addition to instance variables, a morph can have any number of
named <firstterm>properties</firstterm> which can be different for each morph.
</para>
<para>We add two properties here:
</para>
<anchor id="editMorphBehaviorInspector"/>
<screen>self setProperty: #handlesMouseDown: toValue: true.
self setProperty: #mouseButton1Up:localPosition:
   toValue: [:ignoredEvent :ignoredPosition| self color: Color random]
</screen>

<para>These properties are special to the user interface.  You can find
methods with these names in the <literal>Morph</literal> class to see what they
do.
</para>
<para>After selecting the text and <command><emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>o-it</command>, each time you
<userinput>Left-Click</userinput> on the rect it changes color!
</para>
<para>Note that you can no longer move the ellipse by mouse-down on the
rect, because the rect now takes the mouse event.  You have to
mouse-down on the ellipse.  More on this below.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>move/pick up</secondary></indexterm><para>One quick note on <command>Move</command> versus <command>Pick up</command>.  <command>Move</command>
moves a submorph &#8220;within&#8221; its parent.  <command>Pick up</command> grabs a morph
&#8220;out&#8221; of its parent.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d09_002dMove_002dWithin"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-09-Move-Within.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<anchor id="ch06_002d10_002dPickUp_002d2_002dMoveOut"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-10-PickUp-2-MoveOut.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Before we go on, let&#8217;s use an inspector on the ellipse to change
values of a couple of its instance variables.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d12_002dInspectEllipse"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-12-InspectEllipse.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Observe <link linkend="ch06_002d14_002dSetBorderColor">ch06-14-SetBorderColor</link> and <link linkend="editShapeInspector">editShapeInspector</link>. In
the lower pane of the inspector, code can be executed in the context
of the inspected object. <literal>self</literal> refers to the instance. Here
the pane contains code to set the borderWidth and the borderColor.
</para>
<anchor id="editShapeInspector"/>
<screen>self borderWidth: 10.
self borderColor: Color blue
</screen>

<anchor id="ch06_002d14_002dSetBorderColor"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-14-SetBorderColor.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>In the typical case one wants to refine or change behaviors for all
instances of a class.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Building-your-specialized-Morph">
<title>Building your specialized Morph</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>subclass</secondary></indexterm><para>Let&#8217;s make a simple subclass which changes color when
<userinput>Left-Click</userinput>ed.  Create a new class just as we did with Spacewar!
but subclass <literal>EllipseMorph</literal> with <literal>#ColorClickEllipse</literal>.
</para>
<screen>EllipseMorph subclass: #ColorClickEllipse
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'
</screen>
<para>Save the class definition with <userinput>Ctrl-s</userinput>.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>event</primary><secondary>testing</secondary></indexterm><para><userinput>Right-Click</userinput> on the <command>Message Category</command> pane and select
<command>new category...</command>.  This brings up a number of selections and
allows us to create new ones.  Select &#8220;event handling testing&#8221;.
Then add the method <literal>ColorClickEllipse&gt;&gt;handlesMouseDown:</literal>.
</para>
<screen>handlesMouseDown: aMouseButtonEvent
  &quot;Answer that I do handle mouseDown events&quot;
  ^ true

</screen>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>event</primary><secondary>handling</secondary></indexterm><para>Likewise, add a new catagory &#8220;event handing&#8221; and add the other
method we need.
</para>
<screen>mouseButton1Up: aMouseButtonEvent localPosition: localEventPosition
   &quot;I ignore the mouseEvent information and change my color.&quot;
   self color: Color random
</screen>
<para>Now, you have created a new Morph class and can select a
<literal>ColorClickEllipse</literal> from the World Menu <command>New Morph..</command> and
try it out.  These are fun to <userinput>Left-Click</userinput> on.  Make as many as
you want!
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d15_002dColorClickEllipse"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-15-ColorClickEllipse.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Now you know how to specialize an individual morph, or make a whole
new class of them!
</para>

</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Spacewar_0021-Morphs">
<title>Spacewar! Morphs</title>

<sect2 label="">
<title>All Morphs</title>
<para>Previously we defined the actors of the game as subclasses of the very
general <literal>Object</literal> class (See
<link linkend="torpedoClassVariables">torpedoClassVariables</link>). However the game play, the central star,
the ships and the torpedoes are visual objects, each with a dedicated
graphic shape:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>the game play is a simple rectangular area filled with the
  black color,
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>the central star is a fluctuating yellow disk with an orange
  aura,
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>the ships are rotating quadrangles each one painted with a
  different color,
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>a torpedo is a rotating triangle to paint with a different
  color depending on the firing ship.
</para>  
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>Therefore it makes sense to turn these actors into kinds of
<literal>Morph</literal>s, the visual entity of Cuis-Smalltalk. To do so, point a System
Browser to the class definition of each actor, replace the parent
class <literal>Object</literal> by <literal>PlacedMorph</literal><footnote><para>A
<literal>PlacedMorph</literal> is a kind of <literal>Morph</literal> with a supplementary
<literal>location</literal> attribute; so it can be instructed to move, to
scale and to rotate in the screen.</para></footnote>, then save the class definition
with <userinput>Ctrl-s</userinput>.
</para>
<para>For example, the torpedo class as seen in <link linkend="torpedoClassVariables">torpedoClassVariables</link>
is edited as:
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #Torpedo
   instanceVariableNames: 'position heading velocity lifeSpan'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'
</screen>
<para>Moreover, a placed Morph already knows about its position and
orientation on screen &#8211; it can be dragged and moved in the screen and
rotated with the mouse cursor. Therefore the <literal>position</literal> and
<literal>heading</literal> instance variables are redundant and should be
removed. For now we keep it, it will be removed later when we will
know how to replace each of its use cases with its appropriate Morph
counterpart.
</para>
<anchor id="allActorsMorph"/>
<para><emphasis>Edit
<literal>SpaceWar</literal>&#44; <literal>CentralStar</literal> and <literal>SpaceShip</literal>
to be subclasses of the <literal>PlacedMorph</literal> class.</emphasis>
</para>


<para>As explained in the previous sections of this chapter, a morph can be
embedded within another morph. In Spacewar!, a <literal>SpaceWar</literal> morph
instance presenting the game play, it is the <emphasis>owner</emphasis> of the central
star, space ship and torpedo morphs. Put in other words, the central
star, space ships and torpedoes are <emphasis>submorphs</emphasis> of a
<literal>SpaceWar</literal> morph instance.
</para>
<para>The <literal>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;initializeActors</literal> code in <link linkend="initActors">initActors</link> is
 not complete without adding and positioning the central star and
 space ships as submorphs of the Spacewar! game play:
</para>
<anchor id="initFullActors"/>
<screen>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;initializeActors
   centralStar := CentralStar new.
   self addMorph: centralStar.
   centralStar morphPosition: 0 @ 0.
   torpedoes := OrderedCollection new.
   ships := Array with: SpaceShip new with: SpaceShip new.
   self addAllMorphs: ships.
   ships first 
      morphPosition: 200 @ -200;
      color: Color green.
   ships second 
      morphPosition: -200 @ 200;
      color: Color red
</screen>

<para>There are two important messages: <literal>#addMorph:</literal> and
<literal>#morphPosition:</literal>. The former asks to the receiver morph to embed
its morph argument as a submorph, the latter asks to set the receiver
coordinates in its owner&#8217;s reference frame. From reading the code, you
deduce the origin of the owner reference frame is its middle, indeed
our central star is in the middle of the game play.
</para>
<para>There is a third message not written here, <literal>#morphPosition</literal>, to ask
the coordinates of the receiver in its owner&#8217;s reference frame.
</para>
<para>Remember our discussion about the <literal>position</literal> instance
variable. Now you clearly understand it is redundant and we remove it
from the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal> definitions. Each time
we need to access the position, we just write <literal>self
morphPosition</literal> and each time we need to modify the position we write
<literal>self morphPosition: newPosition</literal>. More on that later.
</para>

<!-- refactor ship and torpedo as mobile entity -->
<anchor id="artRefactoring"/></sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>The art of refactoring</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>refactoring</primary></indexterm>

<para>In our <link linkend="newtonModel">newtonian model</link> we explained the
space ships are subjected to the engine acceleration and the gravity
pull of the central star. The equations are described in
<link linkend="motionEquations">motionEquations</link>.
</para>
<para>Based on these mathematics, we wrote the <literal>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;update:</literal>
method to update the ship position according to the elapsed time &#8211;
see <link linkend="spaceShipMechanic">spaceShipMechanic</link>.
</para>
<para>So far in our model, a torpedo is not subjected to the central star&#8217;s
gravity pull nor its engine acceleration. It is supposing its mass is
zero which is unlikely. Of course the <literal>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update:</literal>
method is simpler than the space ship counter part &#8211; see
<link linkend="torpedoMechanic">torpedoMechanic</link>. Nevertheless, it is more accurate and even more
fun that the torpedoes are subjected to the gravity pull<footnote><para>So a
torpedo should come with a mass.</para></footnote> and its engine acceleration; an
agile space ship pilot could use gravity assist to accelerate a
torpedo fired with a path close to the central star.
</para>
<para>What are the impacts of these considerations on the torpedo and space
ship entities?
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>They will share <emphasis>common states</emphasis> as the mass, the
  position, the heading, the velocity and the acceleration.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>They will share <emphasis>common behaviors</emphasis> as the necessary
  computations to update the position, direction, gravity pull and
  velocity.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>They will have <emphasis>different states</emphasis>: a torpedo
  has a life span state while a space ship has fuel tank capacity and
  torpedoes stock states.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>They will have <emphasis>different behaviors</emphasis>: a
  torpedo self destructs when its life span expires, a space ship
  fires torpedoes and accelerates as long as its fuel tank and its
  torpedoes count are not zero.
</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>
<para>Shared state and behaviors suggest a common class.  Unshared states
and behaviors suggests specialized subclasses which embody
the differences.  So let us &#8220;factor out&#8221; the shared elements of
the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal>
classes into a common ancestor class; one more specialized
than the <literal>Morph</literal> class they currently share.
</para>
<para>Doing such analysis on the computer model of the game is part of the
<firstterm>refactoring</firstterm> effort to avoid behavior and state duplications while
making more obvious the common logic in the entities. The general idea of
code refactoring is to rework existing code to make it more elegant,
understandable and logical.
</para>
<para>To do so, we will introduce a <literal>Mobile</literal> class, a kind of
 <literal>PlacedMorph</literal> with behaviors specific to a mobile object
 subjected to accelerations. Its states are the mass, position,
 heading, velocity and acceleration. Well, as we are discussing
 refactoring, the mass state does not really makes sense in our game,
 indeed our mobile&#8217;s mass is constant. We just need a method returning
 a literal number and we can then remove the <literal>mass</literal> instance
 variable. Moreover, as explained previously, a <literal>PlacedMorph</literal>
 instance already know about its position and heading, so we also
 remove these two attributes, although there are common behaviors to a
 Space ship and a torpedo.
</para>
<para>It results in this <literal>Mobile</literal> definition:
</para>
<anchor id="mobileClass"/>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #Mobile
   instanceVariableNames: 'velocity acceleration color'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'
</screen>

<anchor id="refactoryShipTorpedo"/>
<para><emphasis>What should be the refactored definitions of the
<literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal> classes?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>The first behaviors we add to our <literal>Mobile</literal> are its
initialization and its mass:
</para>
<screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;initialize
  super initialize.
  velocity := 0 @ 0.
  acceleration := 0
        
Mobile&gt;&gt;mass
  ^ 1
</screen>
<para>The next methods to add are the ones relative to the physical
calculations. First, the code to calculate the gravity acceleration:
</para>
<anchor id="gravityForce"/>
<screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;gravity
&quot;Compute the gravity acceleration vector&quot;
   | position |
   position := self morphPosition.
   ^ -10 * self mass * owner starMass / (position r raisedTo: 3) * position
</screen>

<para>This method deserves a few comments:
</para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><literal>self morphPosition</literal> returns a <literal>Point</literal>
  instance, the position of the mobile in the owner reference frame,
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>owner</literal> is the <literal>SpaceWar</literal> instance
  representing the game play. It is the owner &#8211; parent morph &#8211; of
  the mobile. When asking <literal>#starMass</literal>, it interrogates its central
  star mass and return its value:
</para>
<screen>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;starMass
   ^ centralStar mass
</screen>
<para>As a side benefit, we can remove the method <literal>starMass</literal>
defined earlier in the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> class.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>In <literal>position r</literal>, the <literal>#r</literal> message asks the radius
  attribute of a point considered in polar coordinates. It is just its
  length. It is the distance between the mobile and the central star.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para><literal>* position</literal> really means multiply the previous
  scalar value with a <literal>Point</literal>, hence a vector. Thus the returned
  value is a <literal>Point</literal>, a vector in this context, the gravity
  vector.
</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
<para>The method to update the mobile position and velocity is mostly the
same as in <link linkend="spaceShipMechanic">spaceShipMechanic</link>. Of course the
<literal>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;update:</literal> and <literal>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update:</literal>
version must be both deleted. Below is the complete version with the
morph&#8217;s way of accessing the mobile&#8217;s position:
</para>
<anchor id="mobileUpdate"/>
<screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;update: t
&quot;Update the mobile position and velocity&quot;
  | ai ag newVelocity |
  &quot;acceleration vectors&quot;
  ai := acceleration * self direction.
  ag := self gravity.
  newVelocity := (ai + ag) * t + velocity.
  self morphPosition:
     (0.5 * (ai + ag) * t squared)
     + (velocity * t)
     + self morphPosition.
  velocity := newVelocity.	
  &quot;Are we out of screen? If so we move the mobile to the other corner
  and slow it down by a factor of 2&quot;  
  (self isInOuterSpace and: [self isGoingOuterSpace]) ifTrue: [
     velocity := velocity / 2.
     self morphPosition: self morphPosition negated]
</screen>

<para>Now we should add the two methods to detect when a mobile is heading
off into deep space.
</para>
<para>But first we define the method <literal>morphLocalBounds</literal> in each of
our Morph objects. It returns a <literal>Rectangle</literal> instance defined in
the Morph coordinates by its origin and extent:
</para>
<anchor id="boundMorph"/>
<screen>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;morphLocalBounds
   ^ -300 @ -300 extent: 600 @ 600

CentralStar&gt;&gt;morphLocalBounds
   ^ Rectangle center: 0 @ 0 extent: self morphExtent

Mobile&gt;&gt;morphLocalBounds
   ^ Rectangle encompassing: self class vertices
</screen>

<anchor id="mobileDeepSpace"/>
<screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;isInOuterSpace
&quot;Is the mobile located in the outer space? (outside of the game
play area)&quot;
   ^ (owner morphLocalBounds containsPoint: self morphPosition) not

Mobile&gt;&gt;isGoingOuterSpace
&quot;is the mobile going crazy in the direction of the outer space?&quot;
   ^ (self morphPosition dotProduct: velocity) &gt; 0
</screen>

<para>As you see, these test methods are simple and short. When writing
Cuis-Smalltalk code, this is something we appreciate a lot and we do not
hesitate to cut a long method in several small methods. It improves
readability and code reuse. The <literal>#containsPoint:</literal> message asks the
receiver rectangle whether the point in argument is inside its shape.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>overriding</primary></indexterm>
<para>When a mobile is updated, its position and velocity are
updated. However the <literal>Mobile</literal> subclasses <literal>SpaceShip</literal> or
<literal>Torpedo</literal> may need additional specific updates. In object
oriented programming there is this special mechanism named
<firstterm>overriding</firstterm> to achieve this.
</para>
<para>See the <literal>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update:</literal> definition:
</para>
<screen>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update: t
   &quot;Update the torpedo position&quot;
   super update: t.
   &quot;orientate the torpedo in its velocity direction, nicer effect
   while inaccurate&quot;
   self heading: (velocity y arcTan: velocity x).
   lifeSpan := lifeSpan - 1.
   lifeSpan isZero ifTrue: [owner destroyTorpedo: self].
   acceleration &gt; 0 ifTrue: [acceleration := acceleration - 500]
</screen>
<para>Here the <literal>update:</literal> method is specialized to the torpedo
specific needs. The mechanical calculation done in <literal>Mobile&gt;&gt;update:</literal>
is still used to update the torpedo position and velocity: this is
done by <literal>super update: t</literal>. We already discussed
<literal>super</literal>. In the context of
<literal>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update:</literal> it means search for an <literal>update:</literal>
method in <literal>Torpedo</literal>&#8217;s parent class, that class&#8217;s parent
and so on until the method
is found, if not a <emphasis>Message Not Understood</emphasis> error is signalled.
</para>
<para>Among the specific added behaviors, the torpedo orientation along its
velocity vector is inaccurate but nice looking. To orient accordingly
the torpedo, we adjust its heading with its velocity vector heading.
</para>
<para>The life span control, the self-destruction sequence, and the engine
acceleration are also handled specifically. When a torpedo is just fired, its
engine acceleration is huge then it decreases quickly.
</para>
<para>With the System Browser pointed to the <literal>Torpedo&gt;&gt;update:</literal>
method, observe the <option>inheritance</option> button. It is light green,
which indicates the message is sent to <literal>super</literal> too. This is
a reminder the method supplies a specialized behavior.  The button
tool tip explains the color hilight meanings within the method&#8217;s text.
When pressing the <option>inheritance</option> button, you browse all
implementations of the <literal>update:</literal> method within this inheritance
chain.
</para>
<anchor id="ch06_002d20_002dTorpedoUpdateInheritance"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch06-20-TorpedoUpdateInheritance.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>We already met an example of overriding when initializing a space ship
instance &#8211; see <link linkend="initSpaceShip">initSpaceShip</link>. In the context of our class
refactoring, the <literal>initialize</literal> overriding spans the whole
<literal>Mobile</literal> hierarchy:
</para>
<anchor id="initMobileHierarchy"/>
<screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   color := Color gray.
   velocity := 0 @ 0.
   acceleration := 0

SpaceShip&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   self resupply

Torpedo&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   lifeSpan := 500.
   acceleration := 3000
</screen>

<para>Observe how each class is only responsible of its specific state
initialization:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">SpaceShip.</emphasis> Its mechanical states are set with the
 <literal>super initialize</literal> and then the ship is resupplied with
 fuel and torpedoes:
</para>
<screen>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;resupply
   fuel := 500.
   torpedoes := 10
</screen>
</listitem><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Torpedo.</emphasis> Inherited mechanical states initialized; add
 self-destroy sequence initialization and acceleration adjusted to
 mimic the torpedo boost at fire up.
</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>
<para>The behaviors specific to each mobile is set with additional
methods. The <literal>SpaceShip</literal> comes with its control methods we
already described previously in <link linkend="shipControls">shipControls</link> and
<link linkend="fireTorpedo">fireTorpedo</link>, of course there is none for a
<literal>Torpedo</literal>.
</para>
<para>Another important specific behavior is how each kind of <literal>Mobile</literal>
is drawn in the game play, this will be discussed in a next chapter on
the fundamentals of Morph.
</para>
<!-- refactoring central star, no need for mass only a behavior -->
<!-- -->
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
