<chapter label="" id="The-Fundamentals-of-Morph">
<title>The Fundamentals of Morph</title>

<blockquote><attribution>Alan Kay</attribution>
<para>Simple things should be simple and complex things should be possible.
</para></blockquote>



<para>What would we expect if we asked for good support for building GUIs in a
programming system?
</para>
<para>In <link linkend="Visual-with-Morph">Visual with Morph</link> we started with that same question, and
gave an overview of Morphs and their interactive behavior. This
chapter deals with how Morphs are built, how to create new Morphs and
what rules they follow.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>moprh</primary><secondary>legacy</secondary></indexterm><para>The User Interface framework in Cuis-Smalltalk is called Morphic. Morphic was
originally created by Randy Smith and John Maloney as the
<ulink url="https://bibliography.selflanguage.org/_static/self4.0UserInterface.pdf">UI
for Self</ulink>. Later, John Maloney ported it to Smalltalk, to be used as
the
<ulink url="http://stephane.ducasse.free.fr/FreeBooks/CollectiveNBlueBook/morphic.final.pdf">UI
for Squeak</ulink>.
</para>



<sect1 label="" id="Going-Vector">
<title>Going Vector</title>

<para>For Cuis-Smalltalk, we built Morphic 3, the third design iteration of these
ideas, after Self&#8217;s Morphic 1 and Squeak&#8217;s Morphic 2. If you already
know Morphic in Self or Squeak, most concepts are similar, although
with some improvements: Morphic 3 coordinates are not limited to being
integer numbers, the apparent size (zoom level) of elements is not
tied to pixel density, and all drawing is done with high quality
(subpixel) anti aliasing. These enhancements are enabled by the huge
advance in hardware resources since Self and Squeak were designed (in
the late 80&#8217;s and late 90&#8217;s respectively). Additionally, careful
design of the framework relieves Morph programmers from much the
complexity that was required, especially with regards to geometry.
</para>
<sect2 label="">
<title>A first example</title>

<para>Let&#8217;s start with some examples. What we want is to build our own
graphic objects, or Morphs. A Morph class is part of the Morph
hierarchy and usually includes a <literal>drawOn:</literal> method for drawing
its distinctive appearance. If we forget about computers for a second,
and consider drawing with color pens on a sheet of paper, one of the
most basic things we can do is to draw straight lines.
</para>
<para>So, let&#8217;s start a System Browser window and build a straight line
object:
</para>
<screen>Morph subclass: #LineExampleMorph
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<para>In method category <command>drawing</command> add:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>vector</secondary><tertiary>line drawing</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>drawOn:</literal></secondary></indexterm><screen>LineExampleMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas strokeWidth: 20 color: Color green do: [
      aCanvas
         moveTo: 100 @ 100;
         lineTo: 400 @ 200 ].
</screen>
<para>Now in a Workspace execute:
</para><screen>LineExampleMorph new openInWorld
</screen>
<para>If you get a prompter asking whether to install and activate Vector
Graphics support, please answer yes. There it is. You have already
built your first <literal>Morph</literal> class.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d01_002dLineDetails"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-01-LineDetails.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>The code is self evident, the <literal>drawOn:</literal> method takes a
<literal>VectorCanvas</literal> instance as an argument. <literal>VectorCanvas</literal>
provides many drawing operations for morphs to use. You can play with
the various drawing operations and their parameters, and see the
result. If you make a mistake, and the <literal>drawOn:</literal> method fails,
you&#8217;ll get a red and yellow error box. After fixing your
<literal>drawOn:</literal> method, do ...World menu &#8594;
<command>Debug...</command> &#8594; <command>Start drawing all again</command>.. to get
your morph redrawn correctly.
</para>
<anchor id="exeCrossMorph"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you modify our
line morph so it draws itself as a cross with an extent of 200
pixels?</emphasis>
</para>



</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Morph you can move</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>movable</secondary></indexterm><para>You might have already tried to click and drag on your Line, like you
can do with regular windows and most other Morphs. If not, try
now. But nothing happens! The reason is that our Morph is fixed in a
place in the owner morph (the WorldMorph). It is fixed because
<literal>drawOn:</literal> says it should be a line between <literal>100 @ 100</literal>
and <literal>400 @ 200</literal>. Moving it around would mean modifying those
points. One possible way to do that could be to store those points in instance
variables.
</para>
<para>But now, we just want to code our morph in the simplest possible way,
and still be able to move it around. The solution is to make it
subclass of <literal>PlacedMorph</literal>, instead of <literal>Morph</literal>.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>delete</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>To do this, first evaluate the code below to get rid of all
LineExampleMorph instances:
</para>
<anchor id="deleteMorphInstances"/>
<screen>LineExampleMorph allInstancesDo: [ :m | m delete]
</screen>

<para>Then, in the System Browser class declaration for LineExampleMorph, type
<literal>PlacedMorph</literal> instead of <literal>Morph</literal> and save. Now execute
again:
</para>
<screen>LineExampleMorph new openInWorld
</screen>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>location</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>You will get a line you can grab with the mouse and move it
around. <literal>PlacedMorph</literal> adds a new instance variable called
<literal>location</literal>. If a morph has a <literal>location</literal>, it can be
moved around, by modifying it. The <literal>location</literal> also defines a
new local coordinate system. All the coordinates used in the
<literal>drawOn:</literal> method are now relative to this new coordinate
system. That&#8217;s why we don&#8217;t need to modify the <literal>drawOn:</literal>
method. <literal>drawOn:</literal> now tells how the morph should be drawn, but
not where. The <literal>location</literal> also specifies a possible rotation
and scale factor. This means that subinstances of <literal>PlacedMorph</literal>
can also be rotated and zoomed.
</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Filled morph</title>
<para>Let&#8217;s build another morph, to have more fun.
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #TriangleExampleMorph
   instanceVariableNames: 'borderColor fillColor'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<para>In method category <command>initialization</command> add:
</para>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   borderColor := Color random alpha: 0.8.
   fillColor := Color random alpha: 0.6.
</screen>
<para>In the <command>drawing</command> method category add:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>vector</secondary><tertiary>filling area</tertiary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>drawOn:</literal></secondary></indexterm><screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas strokeWidth: 10 color: borderColor fillColor: fillColor do: [
      aCanvas
         moveTo: 0 @ 100;
         lineTo: 87 @ -50;
         lineTo: -87 @ -50;
         lineTo: 0 @ 100 ].
</screen>
<para>Take a moment to understand that code, to guess what it will do. Now
execute:
</para>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph new openInWorld
</screen>
<para>Do it several times, and move each triangle around. Each new triangle
you create has different colors. And these colors are not completely
opaque. This means that when you place your triangle over some other
morph, you can see through it.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d02_002dTriangles"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-02-Triangles.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>



<anchor id="exeRectMorph"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you write a
movable rectangle morph with an x,y extent of 200 by 100? The rect will
be filled with a random translucent color and surrounded by a thin
blue line.</emphasis>
</para>


<para>As we learnt previously, Morphic gives you additional ways to interact
with your morphs. With a three button mouse or a wheel mouse, place
the mouse pointer (a <literal>HandMorph</literal> instance) over one of your
triangles and click with the center button or mouse wheel. If you don&#8217;t have
a three button mouse substitute <userinput>Command-click</userinput>. You get a constellation
of small colored circles around your morph. This is called the morph&#8217;s
<firstterm>halo</firstterm>, and each colored circle is a <firstterm>halo
handle</firstterm>. See <link linkend="ch07_002d02_002dTriangles">ch07-02-Triangles</link>.
</para>
<para>At the top left you have the red <command>Remove</command> handle. Clicking on it
just removes the morph from the morphic world. Hover your hand over
each handle, and you&#8217;ll get a tooltip with its name. Other handles let
you <command>Duplicate</command> a morph, open a <command>Menu</command> with actions on it,
<command>Pick up</command> (same as dragging it with the the mouse as you did
before). The <command>Move</command> operation is similar to <command>Pick up</command>, but
doesn&#8217;t remove the morph from the current owner. More about that,
later. The <command>Debug</command> handle opens a menu from where you can open
an Inspector or a Hierarchy Browser to study the morph.
</para>
<para>You also have a <command>Rotate</command> and <command>Change scale</command> handles. Try
them! To use them, move your hand to the handle, and then press the
mouse button and drag it. As you might have guessed, the rotate
handles spins your morph around the center of its surrounding
rectangle. The scale handles controls the apparent zoom
applied to your morph. Both scale and rotation (and also displacement,
as when you move your morph around) are implemented by modifying the
inner coordinate system defined by your morph. Displacement, rotation
and scale are floating point numbers, and thus not limited to
integers.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>rotationCenter</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>To change the center of rotation of a Morph, you override the method
<literal>rotationCenter</literal> accordingly:
</para>
<screen>RectangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;rotationCenter
   ^ 0 @ 0
</screen>
<para>Observe how our rectangle morph now reacts to the rotation handle. We
will learn how to control all this with code and animate our morph.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Animated morph</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>animated</secondary></indexterm><para>Let&#8217;s add two methods to our <literal>TriangleExampleMorph</literal> to
make our triangle <emphasis>alive</emphasis>:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>step,wantsSteps</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>In the method category <command>stepping</command> define:
</para><screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;wantsSteps
   ^ true
</screen>
<para>...and:
</para><screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;step
   fillColor := Color random.
   self redrawNeeded
</screen>
<para>Then create some additional triangles as you did before.
</para>
<para>This will make our triangles change color once a second. But more
interesting, edit the method:
</para>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;stepTime
   ^ 100
</screen>
<para>...and:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>morphPosition</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;step
   self morphPosition: self morphPosition + (0.4@0).
   self redrawNeeded
</screen>
<para>Now, our morph steps ten times per second, and moves to the right at a
speed of four pixels per second. At each step it moves by 0.4 pixels,
and not by an integer number of pixels. High quality anti-aliasing
drawing means we can actually do that! You can make it step at a speed
of four times a second, and move 1 pixel each time, and see how different
that looks.
</para>
<para>Now try this:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>rotateBy:</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;step
   self morphPosition: self morphPosition + (0.2@0).
   self rotateBy: 4 degreesToRadians.
   self redrawNeeded
</screen>
<para>It gets even better. First get rid of all instances:
</para> 
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph allInstancesDo: [ :m | m delete]
</screen>
<para>And modify these methods:
</para>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   borderColor := Color random alpha: 0.8.
   fillColor := Color random alpha: 0.6.
   scaleBy := 1.1
</screen>
<para>Accept <literal>scaleBy</literal> as a new instance variable of the
<literal>TriangleExampleMorph</literal> class.
</para>
<screen>TriangleExampleMorph&gt;&gt;step
   self morphPosition: self morphPosition + (0.2@0).
   self rotateBy: 4 degreesToRadians.
   self scaleBy: scaleBy.
   self scale &gt; 1.2 ifTrue: [scaleBy := 0.9].
   self scale &lt; 0.2 ifTrue: [scaleBy := 1.1].
   self redrawNeeded
</screen>
<para>Then create a new triangle:
</para><screen>TriangleExampleMorph new openInWorld
</screen>
<para>See that when the triangle is doing its crazy dance, you can still
open a halo and interact with it.
</para>



</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Morph in morph</title>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary>submorph</secondary></indexterm>
<para>Now, let&#8217;s try something different. Grab one of your
<literal>LineExampleMorph</literal>. With the halo, zoom it until it is about the
size of your triangle. Now place the triangle above your line. Open a
halo on the triangle, click on the <command>Menu</command> handle and select
...<command>embed into</command> &#8594;
<command>LineExampleMorph</command>. This makes the triangle a submorph of the
line. Now, if you move, scale or rotate the line, the triangle also
gets adjusted.
</para>
<para>You can open a halo on the triangle. To do this, middle-click twice
over it. With the halo on the triangle, you can rotate or zoom it
independently of the line. Also note that when you grab the triangle
with your hand (not using the halo), you grab the
line&#160;+&#160;triangle composite. You can&#8217;t just drag the triangle
away. For this, you need the triangle&#8217;s halo. Use its <command>Move</command>
handle<footnote><para>By now, it is likely that the triangle has walked quite
a bit!</para></footnote> to position it without <emphasis>getting it out</emphasis> of the line. Use
its <command>Pick up</command> handle to take it with the hand and drop
it in the world. Now, the triangle is no a longer submorph of the line,
and the morphs can be moved, rotated or scaled independently.
</para>
<para>But let&#8217;s try something. Make the triangle submorph of the line
again. Now add the following method to category <command>geometry
testing</command> of the class <literal>LineExampleMorph</literal>:
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>clipsSubmorphs</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<screen>LineExampleMorph&gt;&gt;clipsSubmorphs
   ^ true
</screen>
<para>The drawing of the triangle gets cut exactly at the bounds of the
line. This is most useful for implementing scrolling panes that only
make a part of their contents visible, but might have other uses too.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d04_002dAnimatedAndClippedSubmorph"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-04-AnimatedAndClippedSubmorph.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>



</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="A-Clock-Morph">
<title>A Clock Morph</title>
<para>With all the things we have already learned, we can build a more
sophisticated morph. Let&#8217;s build a <literal>ClockMorph</literal> as see in
<link linkend="ch07_002d05_002dClock">ch07-05-Clock</link>.
</para>
<!-- In order to have a default text font based on -->
<!-- vector graphics, do ...@clicksequence{World menu @click{} -->
<!-- @label{Preferences...} @click{} @label{Set System Font...} @click{} -->
<!-- @label{DejaVu...} @click{} @label{DejaVuSans}}@footnote{You can select -->
<!-- any other TrueType font from the ones available.}. -->

<anchor id="ch07_002d05_002dClock"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-05-Clock.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Let&#8217;s create <literal>ClockMorph</literal>, the dial clock :
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #ClockMorph
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>drawOn:</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>...and its drawing method in the category <command>drawing</command>:
</para>
<anchor id="clockDialDrawing"/>
<screen>ClockMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas
      ellipseCenter: 0@0
      radius: 100
      borderWidth: 10
      borderColor: Color lightCyan
      fillColor: Color veryVeryLightGray.
   aCanvas drawString: 'XII' at: -13 @ -90 font: nil color: Color brown.
   aCanvas drawString: 'III' at: 66 @ -10 font: nil color: Color brown.
   aCanvas drawString: 'VI' at: -11 @ 70 font: nil color: Color brown.
   aCanvas drawString: 'IX' at: -90 @ -10 font: nil color: Color brown
</screen>


<para>We create <literal>ClockHourHandMorph</literal>, the hand for the hours:
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #ClockHourHandMorph
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<para>...and its drawing method in the category <command>drawing</command>:
</para>
<screen>ClockHourHandMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas fillColor: (Color black alpha: 0.6) do: [
      aCanvas
         moveTo: 0 @ 10;
         lineTo: -5 @ 0;
         lineTo: 0 @ -50;
         lineTo: 5 @ 0;
         lineTo: 0 @ 10 ].
</screen>
<para>You can start playing with them. We could use several instances of a
single <literal>ClockHandMorph</literal>, or create several classes. Here we
chose to do the latter. Note that all the <literal>drawOn:</literal> methods use
hardcoded constants for all coordinates. As we have seen before, this
is not a limitation. We don&#8217;t need to write a lot of specialized trigonometric and
scaling formulas to build Morphs in Cuis-Smalltalk!
</para>
<para>By now, you might imagine what we are doing with all this, but please
bear with us while we finish building our clock.
</para>
<para>We create <literal>ClockMinuteHandMorph</literal>, the hand for the minutes:
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #ClockMinuteHandMorph
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<para>...and its drawing method in the category <command>drawing</command>:
</para>
<screen>ClockMinuteHandMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas fillColor: ((Color black) alpha: 0.6) do: [
      aCanvas
         moveTo: 0 @ 8;
         lineTo: -4 @ 0;
         lineTo: 0 @ -82;
         lineTo: 4 @ 0;
         lineTo: 0 @ 8 ]
</screen>
<para>And finally, the <literal>ClockSecondHandMorph</literal>, the hand for the seconds:
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #ClockSecondHandMorph
   instanceVariableNames: ''
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Morphic-Learning'
</screen>
<para>...and its drawing method in the category <command>drawing</command>:
</para>
<screen>ClockSecondHandMorph&gt;&gt;drawOn: aCanvas
   aCanvas strokeWidth: 2.5 color: Color red do: [
      aCanvas
         moveTo: 0 @ 0;
         lineTo: 0 @ -85 ]
</screen>
<para>Now, all that is needed is to put our clock parts together in
<literal>ClockMorph</literal>. In its method category <command>initialization</command> add
its <literal>initialize</literal> method (accept the new names as instance
variables):
</para>
<screen>ClockMorph&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   self addMorph: (hourHand := ClockHourHandMorph new).
   self addMorph: (minuteHand := ClockMinuteHandMorph new).
   self addMorph: (secondHand := ClockSecondHandMorph new)
</screen>
<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
If you have not already added instance variables for the
clock hands, the Cuis IDE will note this and ask what you want
to do about it.  We want to declare the three missing names as instance
variables.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d07_002dClockMorph_002dinitialize"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-07-ClockMorph-initialize.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Your <literal>ClockMorph</literal> class definition should now be complete!
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d08_002dClockMorph_002divars_002dadded"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-08-ClockMorph-ivars-added.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>Finally, we animate our clock. In method category <command>stepping</command> add the
method:
</para>
<screen>ClockMorph&gt;&gt;wantsSteps
   ^ true
</screen>
<para>...and:
</para>
<screen>ClockMorph&gt;&gt;step
   | time |
   time := Time now.
   hourHand rotationDegrees: time hour * 30.
   minuteHand rotationDegrees: time minute * 6.
   secondHand rotationDegrees: time second * 6
</screen>
<para>Take a look at how we update the clock hands.
</para>
<para>As we said before, any <literal>PlacedMorph</literal> defines a coordinate
system for its own <literal>drawOn:</literal> method and also for its
submorphs. This new coordinate system might include rotation or
reflexion of the axis, and scaling of sizes, but by default they
don&#8217;t. This means that they just translate the origin, by specifying
where in the owner point <literal>0 @ 0</literal> is to be located.
</para>
<para>The World coordinate system has <literal>0 @ 0</literal> at the top left
corner, with X coordinates increasing to the right, and Y coordinates
increasing downwards. Positive rotations go clockwise. This is the
usual convention in graphics frameworks. Note that this is different
from the usual mathematics convention, where Y increases upwards, and
positive angles go counterclockwise.
</para>
<para>So, how do we update the hands? For example, for the hour hand, one
hour means 30 degrees, as 12 hours means 360 degrees or a whole
turn. So, we multiply hours by 30 to get degrees. Minute and second hand
work in a similar way, but as there are 60 minutes in one hour, and 60
seconds in one minute, we need to multiply them by 6 to get degrees. As
rotation is done around the origin, and the clock has set the origin at its
center (<link linkend="clockDialDrawing">clockDialDrawing</link>), there&#8217;s no need to set the position of the
hands. Their <literal>0 @ 0</literal> origin will therefore be at the clock
<literal>0 @ 0</literal>, i.e. the center of the clock.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d06_002dExerciseClock"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-06-ExerciseClock.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<anchor id="exeFancyClock"/>
<para><emphasis>Look at the clock on
<link linkend="ch07_002d06_002dExerciseClock">ch07-06-ExerciseClock</link>. Don&#8217;t you think its hand for the seconds
decorated with a red and yellow disc is fancy? How will you modify our
clock morph to get this result?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>Create some instances of your clock: <literal>ClockMorph new
openInWorld</literal>. You can rotate and zoom. Look at the visual quality of
the Roman numerals in the clock face, especially when rotated and
zoomed. You don&#8217;t get this graphics quality on your regular
programming environment! You can also extract the parts, or scale each
separately. Another fun experiment is to extract the Roman numerals
into a separate <literal>ClockFaceMorph</literal>, and make it submorph of the
Clock. Then, you can rotate just the face, not the clock, and the
clock will show fake time. Try it!
</para>
<para>You might have noted two things that seem missing, though: How to
compute bounding rectangles for Morphs, and how to detect if a Morph
is being hit by the Hand, so you can move it or get a halo. The
display rectangle that fully contains a morph is required by the framework
to manage the required refresh of Display areas as a result of
any change. But you don&#8217;t need to know this rectangle in order to
build your own Morphs. In Cuis-Smalltalk, the framework computes it as
needed, and stores it in the <literal>privateDisplayBounds</literal>
variable. You don&#8217;t need to worry about that variable at
all.
</para>
<para>With respect to detecting if a Morph is being touched by the Hand,
or more generally, if some pixel belongs to a Morph, truth is that during
the drawing operation of a Morph, the framework indeed knows all the
pixels it is affecting. The <literal>drawOn:</literal> method completely specifies
the shape of the Morph. Therefore, there is no need to ask the programmer
to code the Morph geometry again in a separate method! All that is needed
is careful design of the framework itself, to avoid requiring programmers to
handle this extra complexity.
</para>
<para>The ideas we have outlined in this chapter are the fundamental ones in
Morphic, and the framework is implemented in order to support
them. Morphs (i.e. interactive graphic objects) are very general and
flexible. They are not restricted to a conventional widget library,
although such a library (rooted in <literal>BoxedMorph</literal>) is included
and used for building all the Smalltalk tools.
</para>
<para>The examples we have explored use the <command>VectorGraphics</command>
framework. It includes <literal>VectorCanvas</literal> and <literal>HybridCanvas</literal>
classes. Cuis-Smalltalk also includes the legacy <literal>BitBltCanvas</literal> class
inherited from Squeak. <literal>BitBltCanvas</literal> doesn&#8217;t support the vector
graphics drawing operations and doesn&#8217;t do anti-aliasing or
zooming. But it is mature, and it relies on the BitBlt operation that
is included in the <acronym>VM</acronym>. This means that it offers excellent
performance.
</para>
<para>To further explore Cuis-Smalltalk&#8217; Morphic, evaluate <literal>Feature
require: 'SVG'</literal>, and then <literal>SVGMainMorph exampleLion
openInWorld</literal> and the other examples there. Also, be sure to try the
examples in the class category <command>Morphic-Examples</command>, among them
execute <literal>Sample10PythagorasTree new openInWorld</literal> and play
with the mouse wheel&#8217;s up and down, left and right directions.
</para>
<para>Before we leave this section, here is a two lines change to turn our
Cuis quartz clock<footnote><para>In a quartz clock, the hand for the seconds
moves every second.</para></footnote> to an automatic Swiss clock<footnote><para>In an
automatic clock, the hand for the seconds moves every fraction of a
second. The smaller the fraction, the more premium the clock
is.</para></footnote><footnote><para>A Japanese automatic clock will be just fine too.</para></footnote>:
</para>
<screen>ClockMorph&gt;&gt;stepTime
    ^ 100 &quot;milliseconds&quot;
ClockMorph&gt;&gt;step
../..
   secondHand rotationDegrees: (time second + (time nanoSecond * 1.0e-9))* 6
</screen>
<para>Try to understand how these changes affect the behavior of the
seconds&#8217; hand and at which fraction of a second it is rotating.
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 label="" id="Back-to-Spacewar_0021-Morphs">
<title>Back to Spacewar! Morphs</title>

<sect2 label="">
<title>Central star</title>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>backtick</primary></indexterm>
<para>Our central star has an extent of <literal>30 @ 30</literal> we need to use
in several places in the code. Therefore it makes sense to define a
dedicated method to answer this value:
</para>
<anchor id="centralStarExtent"/>
<screen>CentralStar&gt;&gt;morphExtent
   ^ `30 @ 30`
</screen>

<para>&#160;<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="note.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
An expression surrounded with backticks <literal>'`'</literal> is
evaluated only once, when the method is first saved and compiled.
This creates a compound literal value and improves the performance of
the method since the expression is not evaluated each time the method
is called: the pre-built value is used instead.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>number</primary><secondary>integer</secondary><tertiary><literal>atRandom</literal></tertiary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>drawOn:</literal></secondary></indexterm>
<para>As you learnt previously, a morph draws itself from its
<literal>drawOn:</literal> method. We draw the star as an ellipse with randomly
fluctuating x and y radius:
</para>
<anchor id="centralStarDraw"/>
<screen>CentralStar&gt;&gt;drawOn: canvas
   | radius |
   radius := self morphExtent // 2.
   canvas ellipseCenter: 0 @ 0
      radius: (radius x + (2 atRandom - 1)) @ (radius y + (2 atRandom - 1))
      borderWidth: 3 
      borderColor: Color orange 
      fillColor: Color yellow
</screen>

<para>The star diameters in the x and y directions are fluctuating
independently of 0 to 2 units. The star does not look perfectly round.
</para>


</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Space ship</title>
<para>At the game start-up, the nose of the space ship is pointing to the
top of the screen as seen in <link linkend="ch07_002d10_002dShipDiagram">ch07-10-ShipDiagram</link> and the angle
of its direction is therefore -90&#176;, while the angle of its
rotation is 0&#176;. Remember the Y ordinate are oriented
toward the bottom of the screen.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d10_002dShipDiagram"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-10-ShipDiagram.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>

<para>Then its <literal>drawOn:</literal> method is written as:
</para>
<anchor id="spaceShipDrawing"/>
<screen>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;drawOn: canvas
   | a b c d |
   a := 0 @ -15.
   b := -10 @ 15.
   c := 0 @ 10.
   d := 10 @ 15.
   canvas line: a to: b width: 2 color: color.
   canvas line: b to: c width: 2 color: color.
   canvas line: c to: d width: 2 color: color.
   canvas line: d to: a width: 2 color: color.
   &quot;Draw gas exhaust&quot;
   acceleration ifNotZero: [
      canvas line: c to: 0 @ 35 width: 1 color: Color gray]
</screen>

<anchor id="exeGasExhaust"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you modify
the space ship <literal>drawOn:</literal> method with the gas exhaust drawing
depends on the acceleration rate?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>When there is an acceleration from the engine, we draw a small gray
line to represent the gas exhaust.
</para>
<para>When the user turns the ship, the morph is rotated a bit by adjusting
its heading:
</para>
<screen>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;right
&quot;Rotate the ship to its right&quot;
   self heading: self heading + 0.1

SpaceShip&gt;&gt;left
&quot;Rotate the ship to its left&quot;
   self heading: self heading - 0.1
</screen>

<para>But how does this heading affect the rotation of the morph?
</para>
<para>Underneath, the <literal>MobileMorph</literal> is equipped with an affine
transformation to scale, rotate and translate the coordinates passed as
arguments to the drawing messages received by the canvas. Therefore, our
<literal>heading</literal> methods are defined to match this internal
representation and we use the <literal>rotation:</literal> method from the
<literal>PlacedMorph</literal> class to rotate appropriately. The
<literal>location</literal> attribute represents an affine transformation, and
we get its rotation angle with the <literal>#radians</literal> message.
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>rotation:</literal></secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>morph</primary><secondary><literal>location</literal></secondary></indexterm><screen>Mobile&gt;&gt;heading
   ^ location radians - Float halfPi
Mobile&gt;&gt;heading: aHeading
   self rotation: aHeading + Float halfPi
</screen>
<para>When a mobile is vertical, pointing to the top of the screen, its
heading is -90&#176; (-pi/2) in the screen coordinates
system. In that situation the mobile is not rotated &#8211; or
0&#176; rotated &#8211; therefore we add 90&#176; (pi/2) to
the heading to get the matching rotation angle of the mobile.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Torpedo</title>

<!-- Give the diagram of the torpedo, and as an exercise ask how to code -->
<!-- its drawOn: and morphExtent methods -->

<para>Alike a space ship, when a torpedo is just instantiated its nose
points in the direction of the top of the screen and its vertices are
given by the <link linkend="ch07_002d11_002dTorpedoDiagram">ch07-11-TorpedoDiagram</link>.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d11_002dTorpedoDiagram"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-11-TorpedoDiagram.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<anchor id="exeTorpedoExtent"/>
<para><emphasis>Given the vertices
given by <link linkend="ch07_002d11_002dTorpedoDiagram">ch07-11-TorpedoDiagram</link>&#44; how will you write its
<literal>morphExtent</literal> method?</emphasis>
</para>



<anchor id="exeTorpedoDrawing"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you write
the <literal>Torpedo</literal>&#8217;s <literal>drawOn:</literal> method?</emphasis>
</para>



</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Drawing revisited</title>

<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary>instance variable</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>class instance</secondary></indexterm><!-- refactoring of drawOn: explain class variable -->
<para>As you may have observed, the <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal>
<literal>drawOn:</literal> methods share the same logic: drawing a polygon given
its vertices. We likely want to push this common logic to their common
ancestor, the <literal>Mobile</literal> class. It needs to know about its
vertices, so we may want to add an instance variable
<literal>vertices</literal> initialized in its subclasses with an array
containing the points:
</para>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #Mobile
   instanceVariableNames: 'acceleration color velocity vertices'
   classVariableNames: ''
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'

SpaceShip&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   vertices := {0@-15 . -10@15 . 0@10 . 10@15}.
   self resupply
   
Torpedo&gt;&gt;initialize
   super initialize.
   vertices := {0@-4 . -2@4 . 2@4}.
   lifeSpan := 500.
   acceleration := 3000
</screen>
<para>However this is not a good idea. Imagine the game play with 200
torpedoes, the vertices array will be duplicated 200 times with the
same data!
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect3">Class instance variable</bridgehead>

<para>In that kind of situation, what you want is a <firstterm>class instance
variable</firstterm> defined in the class side &#8211; in contrast to the instance
side where we have been coding until now.
</para>
<para>We make use of the fact that all objects are instances of some class.
The  <literal>Mobile class</literal> is an instance of the class <literal>Class</literal>!
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>A <firstterm>class instance variable</firstterm> can be accessed and assigned
 only by the class itself in a <firstterm>class method</firstterm>.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>An entity (i.e. a fired torpedo) can access class instance
 variables via <firstterm>class methods</firstterm>, by sending a message to a class
 (i.e. <literal>Torpedo</literal>) rather than to itself or some other entity.
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>In the class hierarchy, each subclass has its own instance
 of the class instance variable, and can assign a different value to
 it &#8211; in contrast with a <firstterm>class variable</firstterm> which is shared among
 all the subclasses (discussed later).
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>To edit the <emphasis>class</emphasis> instance variables and <emphasis>class</emphasis>
 methods, in the System Browser press the <command>class</command> button under
 the class list.
</para>
</listitem></orderedlist>
<para>In the System Browser, we click the <command>class</command> button then we
declare our variable in the <literal>Mobile class</literal> definition &#8211;
<link linkend="ch07_002d12_002dbrowserClassSide">ch07-12-browserClassSide</link>:
</para>
<anchor id="instanceVariableMobileClass"/>
<screen>Mobile class
   instanceVariableNames: 'vertices'
</screen>

<para>Then we write an access method in the <literal>Mobile class</literal>, so
<literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal> instances can access it:
</para>
<screen>Mobile class&gt;&gt;vertices
   ^ vertices
</screen>
<anchor id="ch07_002d12_002dbrowserClassSide"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-12-browserClassSide.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>



<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary>initialize</secondary></indexterm><para>Next, each subclass is responsible to correctly initialize
<literal>vertices</literal> with its <literal>initialize</literal> class method:
</para>
<anchor id="initializeClass"/>
<screen>SpaceShip class&gt;&gt;initialize
&quot;SpaceShip initialize&quot;
   vertices :=  {0@-15 . -10@15 . 0@10 . 10@15}

Torpedo class&gt;&gt;initialize
&quot;Torpedo initialize&quot;
   vertices := {0@-4 . -2@4 . 2@4}
</screen>


<para>When a class is installed in Cuis-Smalltalk, its <literal>initialize</literal> class
method is executed. Alternatively select the comment and execute it
with <userinput>Ctrl-d</userinput>.
</para>
<para>Experiment in a Workspace to understand how a class instance
variable behaves:
</para>
<anchor id="classInstanceVar"/>
<screen>SpaceShip vertices.
&#8658; nil 
SpaceShip initialize.
SpaceShip vertices.
&#8658; #(0@-15 -10@15 0@10 10@15) 

Torpedo vertices.
&#8658; nil 
Torpedo initialize.
Torpedo vertices.
&#8658; #(0@-4 -2@4 2@4)
</screen>

<para>This is really the behavior we want: <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and
<literal>Torpedo</literal> instances have a different diagram. However, every
instances of a <literal>SpaceShip</literal> will have the same diagram, referring
to the same <literal>vertices</literal> array (i.e. same location in the
computer memory).
</para>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary><literal>class</literal></secondary></indexterm><para>Each instance asks its class side with the <literal>#class</literal> message:
</para>
<screen>aTorpedo class
&#8658; Torpedo
self class
&#8658; SpaceShip
</screen>
<para>The <literal>Torpedo</literal>&#8217;s <literal>drawOn:</literal> is rewritten to access the
vertices in its class side:
</para>
<screen>Torpedo&gt;&gt;drawOn: canvas
   | vertices |
   vertices := self class vertices.
   canvas line: vertices first to: vertices second width: 2 color: color.
   canvas line: vertices third to: vertices second width: 2 color: color.
   canvas line: vertices first to: vertices third width: 2 color: color
</screen>
<anchor id="exeSpaceShipClassSideDiagram"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you rewrite <literal>SpaceShip</literal>&#8217;s <literal>drawOn:</literal> to use the vertices in its class side?</emphasis>
</para>


<para>So far, we still have this redundancy in the <literal>drawOn:</literal>
methods. What we want is <literal>Mobile</literal> to be responsible to draw the
polygon given a vertices array: <literal>self drawOn: canvas
polygon: vertices</literal>.
</para>
<para>The <literal>SpaceShip</literal> and <literal>Torpedo</literal>&#8217;s <literal>drawOn:</literal> will then
be simply written as:
</para>
<screen>Torpedo&gt;&gt;drawOn: canvas
   self drawOn: canvas polygon: self class vertices

SpaceShip&gt;&gt;drawOn: canvas
   | vertices |
   vertices := self class vertices.
   self drawOn: canvas polygon: vertices.
   &quot;Draw gas exhaust&quot;
   acceleration ifNotZero: [
      canvas line: vertices third to: 0@35 width: 1 color: Color gray]
</screen>
<anchor id="exeDrawMobile"/>
<para><emphasis>How will you
write the <literal>drawOn:polygon:</literal> method in <literal>Mobile</literal>? Tip: use the
iterator <literal>withIndexDo:</literal>.</emphasis>
</para>


<!-- Explain the difference with class variable -->
<bridgehead renderas="sect3">Class variable</bridgehead>
<indexterm role="cp"><primary>class</primary><secondary>variable</secondary></indexterm><indexterm role="cp"><primary>variable</primary><secondary>class</secondary></indexterm>
<para>A <firstterm>class variable</firstterm> is written capitalized in the argument of
<literal>classVariableNames:</literal> keyword:
</para>
<anchor id="classVariableMobile"/>
<screen>PlacedMorph subclass: #Mobile
   instanceVariableNames: 'acceleration color velocity'
   classVariableNames: 'Vertices'
   poolDictionaries: ''
   category: 'Spacewar!'
</screen>

<para>As a class instance variable, it can be directly accessed from the
class side and instances are grant access only with messages send to
the class side. <emphasis role="bold">Contrary</emphasis> to a class instance variable, its
value is common in the whole class hierarchy. 
</para>
<para>In Spacewar!, a class variable <literal>Vertices</literal> will have the same
diagram for a space ship and a torpedo. This is not what we want.
</para>
<screen>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;vertices
   ^ `{0@-15 . -10@15 . 0@10 . 10@15}`
</screen>
<!-- it can be simpler -->
</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Drawing simplified</title>
<para>Using a class variable in the present game design is a bit
overkill. It was an excuse to present the concept of class
variables. If the game came with an editor where the user redesigns
the ship and torpedo diagrams, it would make sense to hold the vertices
in a variable. But our vertices of the space ship and torpedo diagrams
are constant. We do not modify them. As we did with the mass of the
space ship &#8211; <link linkend="methodConstant">methodConstant</link> &#8211; we can use a method returning a
collection, surrounded with backtricks to improve efficiency.
</para>
<anchor id="verticesMethod"/>
<screen>SpaceShip&gt;&gt;vertices
   ^ `{0@-15 . -10@15 . 0@10 . 10@15}`
   
Torpedo&gt;&gt;vertices
   ^ `{0@-4 . -2@4 . 2@4}`
</screen>

<para>Then in the drawing methods, we replace <literal>self class
vertices</literal> by <literal>self vertices</literal>.
</para>
<!-- refactoring of collision with display bounds -->
</sect2>
<sect2 label="">
<title>Collisions revisited</title>
<para>In <link linkend="shipSunCollision">shipSunCollision</link>, we have a very naive approach for collision
between the central star and the ships, based on distance between
morphs. It was very inaccurate.
</para>
<para>In bitmap games, a classic way to deal with collision detection is to
look at the intersections of the rectangles surrounding the graphic
objects. The <literal>#displayBounds</literal> message sent to a morph answers its
bounds in the display, a rectangle encompassing the morph given its
rotation and scale.
</para>
<anchor id="ch07_002d13_002dshipDisplayBounds"/>
<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="ch07-13-shipDisplayBounds.png" format="PNG"></imagedata></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>


<para>When browsing the <literal>Rectangle</literal> class, you learn the
<literal>#intersects:</literal> message tells us if two rectangles overlap. This is
what we need for a more accurate collision detection between the
central star and the space ships:
</para>
<anchor id="accurateCollisionShipsSun"/>
<screen>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;collisionsShipsStar
   ships do: [:aShip | 
      (aShip displayBounds intersects: centralStar displayBounds) ifTrue: [
         aShip flashWith: Color red.
         self teleport: aShip]]
</screen>


<para>Nevertheless we use the VectorGraphics framework, its knows about the
shape of each morph it is rendering. It uses this knowledge for
collision detection at the pixel precision. We rewrite our detection
method simpler with the <literal>#collides:</literal> message:
</para>
<anchor id="accuratePixelCollisionShipsSun"/>
<screen>SpaceWar&gt;&gt;collisionsShipsStar
   ships do: [:aShip | 
      (aShip collides: centralStar) ifTrue: [
         aShip flashWith: Color red.
         self teleport: aShip]]
</screen>

<anchor id="exeAccurateDetection"/>
<para><emphasis>Rewrite the three collision detection methods between space ships, torpedoes and the central star.</emphasis>
</para>

<!-- -->
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
